<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Of the fabrique of the Church and church-mens liuings. By William Tooker Doctor in Diuinitie, his Maiesties chaplaine in ordinarie</title>
            <author>Tooker, William, 1558?-1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 155 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19082</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13818)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19082)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1040:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Of the fabrique of the Church and church-mens liuings. By William Tooker Doctor in Diuinitie, his Maiesties chaplaine in ordinarie</title>
                  <author>Tooker, William, 1558?-1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 132, [4] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melchisedech Bradwood for Iohn Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last two leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="lat">lat</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Benefices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19082:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OF THE FABRIQVE of the Church and Church-mens <hi>liuings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By WILLIAM TOOKER Doctor in Diuinitie, his Maieſties Chaplaine in ordinarie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>AVGVST. Pſal. 34.</bibl>
               <l>Quare in praeciſione vultis magnificare nomen Domini?</l>
               <l>Quare duos populos ex vno vultu faecere?</l>
            </q>
            <p>Why will you in praeciſeneſſe magnifie the name of the Lord? Why will you make two peoples vnto him of one?</p>
            <figure>
               <p>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE.</p>
               <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Melchiſedech Bradwood</hi> for <hi>Iohn Norton.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19082:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <label>1</label>
               <item>Of Paritie and Imparitie of gifts.</item>
               <label>2</label>
               <item>Of Competencie and Incompetencie of mens liuings, and of the rewards of mens gifts or maintenance ſo called.</item>
               <label>3</label>
               <item>Of Parity and Imparity of mens liuings, which ariſeth out of the aequalitie or inequalitie of mens gifts, and of prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo called.</item>
               <label>4</label>
               <item>Of ſingularity and pluralitie of Benefices, and of the cauſe thereof, <hi>videlicet,</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſations.</item>
               <label>5</label>
               <item>Of the friends and enemies of Pluralities.</item>
               <label>6</label>
               <item>Of ſupportance and keeping of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brique of the Church vpright.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19082:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST MIGHTIE PRINCE IAMES by the grace of God King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the <hi>Faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, in all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie I offer to your learned cenſure, the fruits of my labour, the firſt fruits whereof, as likewiſe of my dutiful diſpoſition ſeuen yeeres before your Maieſties comming, as meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of my deuoted affection, I ſent into <hi>Scotland</hi> to meet with
<pb facs="tcp:19082:3"/> you, as it were a farre of: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I preſented you with a Booke at my waiting vpon you in your late progreſſe: And now againe, in time of Parliament, and Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node, the time of repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all our Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth I haue preſumed of the like gracious acceptance, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my ſelfe that nothing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth amiſſe to you of ſcholaſtical exerciſe, that tendeth to <hi>vnion,</hi> or to nouriſhing a fellowſhip and <hi>communion</hi> in Eccleſiaſticall or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill affaires. It remaineth that I giue, dedicate, and addict my ſelfe and all my ſtudies to your Highneſſe ſeruice: I reſume often into my hands your <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and weighing the ponderous ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences
<pb facs="tcp:19082:3"/> of that Booke, I finde none to import more good to the Church, then that golden ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or rather incomparably more precious then all the golde of Ophyr, in the 41. page of that Booke: parity <hi>the mother of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and enimy to vnitie, which is the mother of order:</hi> That is, parity in the Church once eſtabliſhed in the gouernement Eccleſiaſticall, will draw on paritie in the politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or ciuill eſtate. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof hath occaſional<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lead me into this diſcourſe, as I thinke not vnrequiſit at this time, in which parity is ſo much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded: Your Maieſtie knoweth by particular experience who they are that hate all eminencie of
<pb facs="tcp:19082:4"/> gifts, and praeeminency of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and miſlike (vnleſſe it be in themſelues all gouernment and ſuperioririe, who they are that would aequall the Scepter of their Presbyterie, or rather aduance it aboue the Scepter of Princes, who they are that haue filled all the world full of needleſſe contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, called all things in quaeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the church diſcipline, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the higheſt Cherubins, to the loweſt pin of the tabernacle, who they are which reproch all iuriſdiction of Biſhops, though it be the very ſame that was in the time of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the great, <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> and other godly Princes times, and contemne all degrees of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities &amp; other digniteis of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall
<pb facs="tcp:19082:4"/> Churches: who they are that would take away all plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and maintenance of learned men, and reduce all inaequalities to an aequalitie, and are profeſſed enemies to the Hierarchy of the Church, and would bring all to popularitie, or Democracy, and afterwards to Anarchie, if their deſignes might take effect and place. Looke what pleaſure or paines they take of the faction in demolition of churches, whether it be by hand, or hand-writing, ſo much or a great deale more, my delectation &amp; trauel is according to my ſmall talent, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, and vpholding of the fabrique of the ſame. Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie as a Chriſtian <hi>Atlas</hi> muſt
<pb facs="tcp:19082:5"/> beare the whole frame, wee of your clergy as ſupporters. Moſt matters are wel calmed with your good moderation (if no after tempeſt doth ariſe) as my hope is and praier to almightie God for the perpetuitie of the peace of Gods Church, and for your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties and your royall iſſues happie preſeruation. London. 2. <hi>Aprill.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maiesties moſt humble Chapleine <hi>W. TOOKER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19082:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>OF PARITIE and imparitie of <hi>mens gifts.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N common expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of this life, &amp; in the vſuall traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke of mens wits, whether it bee in Church or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weale, is moſt clearely ſeene, as in a Chryſtall glaſſe, the great diuerſitie of mens gifts; <hi>Mens,</hi> becauſe they are giuen vnto men; <hi>Gods</hi> neuertheleſſe, as deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God, who although he owe vs nothing, yet beſtoweth all things of his abundant bountie and ſuperabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace. In contemplation and view of ſo many gratious gifts ſhining round about vs, no man may grudge
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19082:6"/> or complaine againſt his God, that he hath giuen him nothing; for the poo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt wretch is inriched with ſome por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſubſtance of his grace: no one can glorie or bragge, no not the richeſt of his creatures, Angels and Archangels, that they haue receiued all things.</p>
            <p>This infinit varietie and garniſh of Gods gifts doth ſhew it ſelfe euerie where, but no where ſo much reſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſheth as in the Garden or <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of Gods Church heere vpon earth mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; whereby we may gather what is the glorious gliſtering of the Church triumphant: There are diuerſities of gifts,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> but it is the ſelfe-ſame ſpirit, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of adminiſtrations, but it is the ſelfe-ſame Lord; diuers maners of operations, but it is the ſelfe-ſame God which worketh all in all: and all this is giuen to profit withall or edification, which is all in all. To one is giuen the word of Wiſdome; to another, the word of Knowledge; to another, Faith healing, Power operatiue, Propheſie, Diſcerning of ſpirits; to other, diuers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19082:6"/> kinds of tongues, or interpretation of tongues: and the Spirit that worketh in euerie one, diuideth to euerie one euen as he will. To ſome one man are giuen two, or three, or fiue talents of the grace of God, to be well vſed and to be employed to Gods glory, becauſe they are the talents of his Sanctuarie: and when a man commeth to make his audit, the account will be heauie to be made, if the occupier be either a ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnthriftie ſeruant or an euill ſtorer. The incomparable excellency of all ſuch gifts doth eftſoones draw me to the admiration of the gifts, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the praiſe of God the giuer, who hath giuen ſuch gifts to men, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to diſdaine or reproch the men whom God himſelfe hath honoured with ſuch high titles, inueſted with ſuch ſacred functions and offices gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly vouchſafed of ſuch praeeminent gifts which are for the honour and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of himſelfe, leaſt of all to equall all thoſe men in matter of preferment, whom Gods owne right hand hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen a precedencie, and made inferiour
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19082:7"/> and vnequall one vnto another by a certaine prerogatiue of his celeſtiall gifts.</p>
            <p>This is certaine, God neuer gaue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch gifts, but he would haue them to be honored; and it is as certaine, the gifts are diuers which are to be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: which becauſe I would haue it the plainer to appeare, I will inlarge a little more of the diuerſitie of mens gifts, to make a way to that which followeth in this ſhort Diſcourſe of competencie and incompetence of mens liuings, which is called maintenance; and of equalitie and inequalitie of liuings, which is termed preferments; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> of ſingularitie and pluralitie of Benefices, and of the cauſe thereof, which is Diſpenſation; and laſtly, of the enemies and friends of the ſame. As in a great Lords or Princes houſe, ſo it is in the Church of God, which is Gods houſe, there are diuers offices and diuers ſeruices, and euery one is promoted to an higher or lower place, according to the qualitie of his deſerts and gifts; whereupon groweth ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19082:7"/> or inferioritie in euery well-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plined houſe.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Oeconomie</hi> of the Church there are many orders and degrees of men all tending from imperfection vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to perfection, that the man of God may be made perfect. Some excell one another in the ſame gift: Some, and thoſe few, excel in all thoſe gifts. Some are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nouices new planted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and newly implanting others. Some, whoſe praiſe is in the Goſpel by long continuance and well deſeruing: God forbid all ſhould be proportioned to one and the like reward. Some Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, able to giue milke and not ſtrong meat; other, both milke and ſtrong meat.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. c. 3. Heb. 5.12.13.14. v.</note> I haue nouriſhed you with milke and not with meat: ſome haue need of milke, and not of ſtrong meat. Euery one that vſeth the milke of Catechiſme or inſtruction is vnskilfull of the word of righteouſneſſe, for he is a babe in Chriſtianitie, but ſtrong meat belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to them that are ſtrong or perfect, euen thoſe which by reaſon of vſe, haue their wittes exerciſed to diſcerne
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19082:8"/> both good and euill.</p>
            <p>The Church of Chriſt alwaies had Readers, Catechiſts, Preachers: by Readers, I meane not onely Readers in Diuinitie controuerſiall, ſuch as are in the Vniuerſities; but Readers of the Scriptures, which is an inferior office: And Catechiſts, whether you take Catechiſme for generall inſtruction, or for ſummarie teaching of the Articles and principles of faith, which is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious kinde of preaching, ſuch as <hi>Deogratias</hi> and <hi>Heraclas</hi> at Carthage, and alſo Preachers of the word, which is a more honourable calling: Who will gaine-ſay theſe to be all woorthy of reward? Who will ſay them to be deigned or thought woorthie of the like reward? The Apoſtles had their Deacons, the Apoſtolicall men their Euangeliſts companions and fellow labourers: the ancient Biſhops their aſſiſtants and coadiutours, but they had not the like honor and the ſame reward. Neither is it probable they had the like gifts 13. <hi>Act.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.</note> in the Church which was at Antioch,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19082:8"/> there were certaine prophets and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, as <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Simon</hi> that was called <hi>Niger;</hi> and <hi>Lucius,</hi> and <hi>Manahen</hi> and <hi>Saul;</hi> doubtleſſe their gifts were diuers, and inequall the one to the other. Yea the Apoſtles themſelues were not indued with knowledge and other gifts all alike; ſome of them are ſaid to be <hi>Columnae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.9. v. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Cephas</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> pillars of the Church; <hi>Paule</hi> planted; <hi>Apollo</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the Church of God: <hi>Apollo</hi> is ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, mightie or powerfull and eloquent, or skilfull or ful of perſwaſion in the Scriptures, but <hi>Paule</hi> as a wiſe architect or builder of the Church, or to lay the foundations of many Churches, and to take care of many congregations, or labour more then all. The more laborious the workeman is, the more woorthy of the greater reward; according to the gift and grace of God men doe labour in the worke of the Lord. Euen as it is in the hoſte of heauen or firmament of his power, one ſtarre differeth from another in glory, and yet all ſtarres of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19082:9"/> whatſoeuer magnitude, are <hi>Vaſa lucis,</hi> veſſels full of light; ſo is it in the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy of his Church; all Miniſters &amp; Paſtors, and Teachers are profitable inſtruments and neceſſary implements of the ſame houſe, although not all of the ſame honour and dignitie, nor equall one to other in place or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, or like ſuperioritie, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with paritie or idenditie of Gods gifts: yet all repleniſhed in ſome meaſure with fulneſſe, as ſanctified veſſels with the light of Gods grace: The diuerſitie of gifts are in all ſorts of men of great multiplicity and variety, and euery one hath not all but as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God to diſpenſe to euery one: and therefore the like inaequalitie may be amongſt Miniſters, as amongſt other men. Now albeit S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſetteth downe <hi>As it were a certaine Idaea or a perfect ſamplar</hi> of an abſolute Miniſter for all to aime vnto the ſame, yet I nothing doubt many more come ſhort, then attaine vnto the ſame, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. <hi>v.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, If a man be without reprehenſion or blame, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19082:9"/> husband of one wife, hauing faithfull children, not accuſable of riot or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractable, for a Biſhop muſt be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe or without reprehenſion, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, able to exhort in ſound doctrine, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to conuince the gain-ſaier: S. <hi>Paule</hi> vſeth the word thriſe, 1. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3. A Biſhop muſt be blameleſſe or without reprehenſion, that is, both for his doctrine and gifts, and for his life and conuerſation, and ſo in the worde <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Biſhop, includeth all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who muſt be perfectly endued with all the enablements by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in that &amp; other places largely deſcribed: yet againe, who doth not know that euery Biſhop and Miniſter cannot be of perfecteſt knowledge and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable gifts which are there requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as in the point of perfection or that which is Superlatiue, which can agree but to one. Are all Prophets? Are all Doctors? doe all ſpeake with tongues? Do all interpret? My Illatiue therefore is that of neceſſitie, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters euery where which are tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19082:10"/> of the people, whether in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of beliefe or of vertuous life and the knowledge of the ſame, can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruct nor teach, but according to the proportion of their own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and of their owne gifts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are endued: And for all to attaine to the point of perfection of gifts is a thing incredible, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame gift is a matter impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and neuertheleſſe, they may co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet after and ſeeke for the beſt gifts, at leſt ſet before their eies as imitable and admirable, the Idaea or ſampler of a Biſhop or Miniſter, furniſhed or enriched with all theſe gifts: Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching degrees of learning and other requiſites for the Miniſtery, it is worth the while to conſider, and weigh that which Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> hath profeſſedly diſputed and written of the ſame:<note place="margin">Hierony. ad Oceanu. ep. <hi>83.</hi>
               </note> As Orators and Philoſophers (faith he) when they deſcribe what Orator and Philoſopher they would wiſh to haue, do none iniury to <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> or <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> (who perhaps are not ſo perfect) but deſcribe the things without the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19082:10"/> perſons: So in the deſcription of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and in the expoſition of thoſe things that be written, <hi>a glaſſe Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij</hi> of Prieſthood or Miniſtery is ſet before vs. In that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (ſaith he) requireth a Biſhop without a fault, or without reprehenſion; he compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth in one all vertues, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth almoſt a thing <hi>Contrary to nature.</hi> And ſpeaking of variety of gifts of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall men,<note place="margin">Hierony. l. <hi>1.</hi> ad Pelag. c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> (he ſaith) Many doe treat well vpon the Goſpels, but in expounding the Apoſtle, are not like themſelues: others that very well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the new Teſtament, yet in the Pſalmes and old Teſtament are dumbe: This I ſay (ſaith S. <hi>Hierom</hi>) becauſe euery one cannot doe all. And againe, God hath giuen diuerſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and manifold vertues, all which euery of vs cannot haue at once. So it commeth to paſſe, that which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and perfect in ſome, is in other but in part: And he that hath not all, is not blameable, nor condemned for that he hath not, but iuſtified &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for that he hath. An inſtance
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19082:11"/> he giueth of this in Biſhops and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: Truely God would haue all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Miniſters to be ſuch as the veſſell of Election teacheth them to be. Firſt, in that he ſaith, a Biſhop muſt be without fault; either there is none ſuch, or a very rare man: Who is there that hath not ſome wart or ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in a body otherwiſe faire, as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> himſelfe had: then to be the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of one wife, ſober, &amp;c. admit you do find them; that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he that can teach, with the other vertues <hi>ye ſhall hardly finde:</hi> I am of opinion you ſhall hardlie finde ſuch as ſhall be accuſed of none: eſpecially yee ſhall hardly finde him that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, able to reſiſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, or conuince erronious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. So that <hi>there is none, or hee is very rare,</hi> that hath all that a Biſhop ought to haue, and yet though one or two things in the catalogue of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops vertues be wanting, he ſhall not thereupon want the name of a iuſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or fit, neither ſhall be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for that he hath not, but ſhall be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19082:11"/> crowned for that he hath: for <hi>to haue all and want nothing,</hi> is his peculiar ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue who ſinned not, and in whoſe mouth is found no guile. To want ſome one or other gift, is ordinary; to be equall or matches one to another, is rare and extraordinary; to excel one another, is commendable; to be infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour and one beneath the other, is not diſpraiſable; to be an exact Preacher and Pulpit-man, is profitable to the Church: ſcant ſhall you find two men of the ſame gift; ſome haue gracefull eloquution &amp; vtterance, or a ſweet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance; ſome others, ſubtiltie and ſharpeneſſe of wit; ſome make great ſhew of Reading and Learning; ſome are able to anatomize the conſcience; ſome better moue and ſtirre vp affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſome the gift of explication; ſome of application: all trees are not of one growth or proceritie, all fruits of one ripeneſſe and maturitie, all flowers of one hue and beautie. All Students in an Vniuerſity of one ſtanding and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie, all Miniſters of one degree of learning, or of one qualitie in gifts, or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19082:12"/> in coequality of the preferment apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to the gifts, my collection is out of the parity and imparity of mens gifts, and ſo by conſequence of mens deſerts riſeth the equality or inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mens liuings: howbeit, all muſt haue competencies; of which I will treat in the next place.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of competencie and incompetencie of mens liuings.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is commonly deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what is a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent liuing for a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Word, and what is incompetent, and what is the cauſe of ſuch incompetencie, and whether if any mans liuing be incompetent and inſufficient, ſomewhat may be drawen or deriued from other men their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes and ſufficiencies, and the ſame added to the inſufficiencie and ſmall maintenance of another: and ſo to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodat and fit all men as <hi>Procustes</hi> did his bed for men of all ſtatures by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19082:12"/> cutting of ſome, and ſtretching out the ſhorteſt to the length of the other.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Competencie</hi> of eſtate and the benefit of contentation, is a matter ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally preſcribed vnto all, whether they be of Laity or Clergy, of high or low degree, Counſeller or meane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Prince or ſubiect, and deſcribed by the Apoſtle, hauing <hi>victum &amp; vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> food and raiment, let vs therewith be content. Wherein the rule is, Let euery man ſtay or remaine in the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling whereunto he is called, and not aſpire higher or aboue his degree, as the faſhion of ſome is, to towre loftier ſtill with the wings of reſtleſſe ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and Diuines of all other muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour themſelues to attaine the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of this contentation, not deſirous of filthie lucre or vnmeaſurable pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes, or ſtudying nothing els; from which imputations I thinke they are freeſt of all men: for if we looke into their priuate eſtates, ſo many paiments ordinarily in a maner iſſuing out of their liuing, their hoſpitalitie extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the vttermoſt of their abilitie,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19082:13"/> their pouertie euery where ſhewing it ſelfe with naked face, before and after their deceaſes; inſomuch, that if any of them thriue through his induſtrie, alwaies forepriſed the bleſſing of God, all their deſire and prouidence is, but to ſaue themſelues from reproche of the world and ſtarke beggerie. And I ſee no cauſe they ſhould not make ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prouiſion for themſelues and their familie, and thriue in the feare of God, being free and no bond-men, being ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and no aliens from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth in which they liue.</p>
            <p>But to returne where I was, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apparent digreſſion. All the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, What is a competent liuing, and what is incompetent and vnfit for a man of the Church? And whether this competencie conſiſt in the quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and number of Benefices, as of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or in the qualitie or goodneſſe of a Benefice, as of one? And whether that Benefice which is fit for one able and ſufficient Miniſter, be alſo competent and fit for another ſomewhat inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter perſon, hauing the ſame eſſence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19082:13"/> or being in the Miniſtery, becauſe they are both ſayd to be of one coat: And further, what ſquare or meaſure euery one that ſhalbe ſo promoted to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent liuing ſhall be meaſured by? And laſtly, who ſhalbe Iudge of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petencie and incompetencie, as of the whole matter?</p>
            <p>To beginne with that firſt, which I propoſed laſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: The Iudge of all this muſt be the <hi>Law,</hi> or the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate who is <hi>Lex loquens,</hi> I meane the ſupreame Magiſtrate who is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſed in all Eſtates, the Prince and other Iudges and Miniſters of Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Lawes; for if euery man ſhould be Iudge, and not according to Lawes on this behalfe prouided, we ſhould haue an olde a doe to accommodate euery man.</p>
            <p>Now for the Law, it hath alreadie defined who ſhal haue a Benefice, with cure of ſoules, whoſe clearely value is thirtie pound and aboue: and who ſhall haue vnder the value aforeſayd; <hi>videlicet,</hi> a Preacher duelie qualified with gifts, authorized to preach by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19082:14"/> the Biſhop, or either of the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or graduated in Diuinitie, or ſhall enioy a Benefice of thirtie pound, or aboue that value: and for other Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices vnder that value, men of meaner gifts, and of vnder deſerts, may obtaine the ſame. All which is ſo well ſetled already, that it needeth no innouation which is dangerous, nor further limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation or reſtriction which is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, if eſpecially this be well loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto and executed by the Fathers of the Church and Spirituall Iudges, all is well. As for the norme or ſquare whereby they ſhall be ſquared alway, is the paritie and imparitie of mens gifts and merits, obſeruing by the way this for a rule, Where no exception is to be taken to the life and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the man, admitting they are both to be preferred to a competent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and both honeſt and godly men, the learneder of the two muſt carry it away. And in caſe the liuing <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> be meane or ſmall, it may be competent and fit for a meane learned man: for if it be abſolutely incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19082:14"/> it is fit for no man: and to make all mens liuings competent a like, and to range them in an equalitie, is a work of the wiſeſt man aliue, whether the proportion of equalitie proue to be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmeticall or Geometricall, it ſhalbe a worke to buſie the wiſeſt man.</p>
            <p>To come therefore to that which was principally propoſed and in the firſt place, What is a competent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for an Eccleſiaſticall man: I doubt not, if you ſhould aſſemble an hundred men, they may chance to proue of an hundred mindes: <hi>Quot ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pita tot ſenſa:</hi> So many men ſo many mindes. How often haue I heard it blaterated by diuers new-fangled fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that fortie or perhaps fiftie, or at the vttermoſt an hundred pound is ſufficient for an honeſt man, or for the honeſteſt of vs all. And by an honeſt man, as they weigh in their ballance of conſideration Honeſty it ſelfe, they meane the graueſt Diuine, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedeſt Preacher, the profoundeſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of longeſt ſtudy and continuance: ſo that by this proportion, if the moſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19082:15"/> reuerend Father of the Primitiue Church were aliue, the learnedeſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the auncient flouriſhing Church, the excellenteſt Doctor and painfulleſt Paſtours were conuerſant amongſt them, ſuch as <hi>Cyprian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> a Biſhop and Martyr, ſuch as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> the golden mouthed Doctor, ſuch as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Millaine,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantia</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> a man of incomparable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie &amp; paines taking in the church, or as <hi>S. Austin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frique,</hi> and an hundred more whom I could rehearſe, were amongſt them if <hi>S. Hierome</hi> who was a Presbyter, and: no Biſhop, termed <hi>Magister orbis ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum,</hi> were at their finding, or to be preferred by them: if all the famous men for writing or preaching were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, they muſt haue but a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing competent &amp; fitting one of their honeſt men, and muſt not haue a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for men of their eſtate. There is no reſpect to be had to their Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall honour or Doctorall degree, or to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19082:15"/> any termes of hoſpitalitie, or to their attendance &amp; familie, or other things coincident to their callings or eſtate, or to the furniſhing or increaſing of their Librarie, which ſome yeeres may chance to coſt them the whole or halfe profits of their benefice: The Miniſter or Paſtour of what qualitie ſoeuer, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duat or vngraduat, muſt haue no more than one of their honeſt men, the reſt muſt be exonerat ſome other way, as matter of ſuperfluitie.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19082:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of paritie or equalitie and imparitie of mens liuings.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom parity or imparity of mens gifts ſpringeth parity or imparity of mens liuings; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuolent and iniurious to allot an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in the aſſignment of Church li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, yet none I hope ſhall be found ſo vnconſcionable to allow that which is abſolutely incompetent for an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall liuing. A neceſſary proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt be made for all, and this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime or rule is generall: He that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth about holy things, may eat of the things of the Temple; euen ſo the Lord hath commanded thoſe which preach the Goſpell, to liue on the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. He that waiteth on the altar, muſt liue on the altar or partake with altars oblations. No man planteth a vineyard,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> but eateth of the fruit. No man feedeth a flocke, but eateth of the milke of his flocke. No man goeth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19082:19"/> to this Spirituall warfare at his owne charge.<note place="margin">Deut. 25.4.</note> The law of Nature teacheth this, <hi>and Moſes law alſo,</hi> Thou ſhalt not muzzle the mouth of the oxe that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the corne. Hath God care of oxen and hath he not much more care of men? If we ſow ſpirituall things, we are worthy of carnall. Conſent of all nations is the law of Nature. In the Schoole of Naturall reaſon this is taught: They that watch ouer vs, and labour for vs, muſt be recompenſed by vs. For this cauſe we pay tribute vnto Kings; wages or ſtipends vnto Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; ſalary vnto Iudges; tithes vnto Clergy-men: becauſe the King gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all; the Souldier fighteth for all; the Iudge or learned Lawyer heareth &amp; determineth all; the Leuite &amp; Prieſt prayeth for &amp; preacheth vnto all, cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſeth &amp; inſtructeth all. Let him that is catechized make him that catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth partaker in all his goods or in all good things.<note place="margin">Gal. 6.6. v.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom ſuper</hi> 3. <hi>Mallachy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierony. ſuper <hi>3.</hi> Mal.</note> 
               <hi>Quod qui facere noluerit, Domini fraudat &amp; ſupplantat.</hi> He that will not do this, defraudeth God, &amp;c. We muſt giue
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19082:20"/> to God that which is Gods:<note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>129.</hi> ſerm. ſuper eum locum.</note> giue vnto Caeſar that which is Caeſars. There is no nation ſo barbarous that will robbe his Gods, no people or generation ſo pernicious and hurtfull to godlineſſe, that wil profeſſedly robbe the ſeruants and Miniſters of his or their God.</p>
            <p>Tithes, oblations, donations are not the goods, or debts of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Clergy as they are either good or bad Clergie-men, but as they are, ſimply Clergie-men: vnleſſe therefore Chriſtian men will be worſe than hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, they are bound in conſcience and conſtrained by the law of God, to pay their due to Gods Miniſters, that God may for paiment of the tenth part ſend downe his bleſſing vpon the other nine parts: eſpecially open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauen and powre downe his ſpirituall raine and bleſſing. This matter being controuerſileſſe, That tithes praediall and perſonall of all and euery ſort belong to Church-men by all lawes; that lands, and glebes, and houſes, as to the Leuites of olde, cities, and ſuburbes and fields; ſo to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19082:20"/> of the New teſtament, by the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie and endowments of Princes and other zealouſly deuoted perſons appertaine, all which maketh for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie and eſtabliſhment of good things thorowout all generations, and for a thankeful reknowledgement that we haue all receiued theſe and many moe good things from the hand of heauen I will inſiſt no longer in this matter, whereof all books diuine and humane, all ſtories Eccleſiaſticall and prophane are full fraught.</p>
            <p>Sithence therefore no queſtion is to be ſtirred about this, <hi>videlicet,</hi> That a portion of our ſubſtance is due to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church and to ſuch as attend the ſeruice of God: it will rather be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned, <hi>What portion is due, and how it ſhould be proportioned</hi> which is payable to the Miniſters, whether to all alike it ought to be equally diſtributed, ſith all are equally Miniſters touching the eſſence of the Miniſtery, and do all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter about holy things; or whether ſome muſt haue more, and ſome leſſe, ſith all are one mans ſeruants, that is,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19082:21"/> God and man, the man Ieſus Chriſt, And whether it be not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an acceptation of perſons or iniuſtice for <hi>Aequalibus inaequalia tribuere aut in aequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus aequalia,</hi> to diſtribute to thoſe who are equall vnequall things, or to vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall perſons equall things; that is to accept the perſons of men, which is an <hi>oppoſite</hi> and repugnant to diſtributiue Iuſtice. Firſt heare, that it may be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtood, in laying out the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and caſting forth the line and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell of this diſtribution of liuings of the Church, the eye of ciuill or eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Iuſtice muſt bee fixed vpon the magnitude or exiguitie, vpon the greatneſſe or ſmallneſſe of mens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that he that meriteth more ſhould alwayes haue more, he that meriteth leſſe ſhould haue leſſe reward: of which equalitie the Law it ſelfe ought to be the keeper and obſeruer. And this may be termed a <hi>proportionable</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie, not abſolute nor Arithmetical which is very neere Anabaptiſticall, which diſtinction is once fit to be layd downe, becauſe there is often vſe of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19082:21"/> the ſame in the buſineſſe now in hand. Benefices Eccleſiaſticall, are like in this to Benefices Military or ſecular. For as ſuch are giuen to ſouldiors and ſeruiters in the warre for their faithfull and truſtie ſeruices, ſo theſe Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall or ſacred Benefices to men or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined to the Miniſterie for the better execution of their ſacred Miniſterie and holy offices, and are alſo remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations of their painefull ſtudies: In Militarie affaires, all that ſerued re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not one and the ſame reward: but different honour, wages, or ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, more or leſſe pay: a common ſouldior had not like entertainement to a Captaine, to a Lieutenant or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell and the reſt, in and after ſeruice done, the Generall of the field or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour diuided vnto them as euerie man was more or leſſe forward or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious: witneſſes vnto this (after the battell) the maner of the auncient Romanes, which was <hi>Ob ciues ſeruatos,</hi> for Citizensſaued in time of warres, to giue garlands <hi>or crownes,</hi> ſome laurell, other of oken leaues, or holme or ſuch
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19082:22"/> like, ſome of golde, or to giue orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as iewels, chaines, beſides the ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend or pay due vnto them:<note place="margin">Virgil. aurea pectoribus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa monili pendent.</note> Now yee know the ſervice of God is called a warfare, &amp; none ought to go this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare on his owne charge, but muſt be prouided for by the Church, which Church is a vineyard: euery dreſſer of a vineyard is not of like skill &amp; indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie. The Church is a flocke, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter a ſhepheard, but all ſhepheards haue not like hire or wages, or are of like deſert or paines taking; <hi>Iacob</hi> kept <hi>Labans</hi> ſheepe &amp; his own; and for his painful ſeruice had double reward and encreaſe of reward. Some flocks are greater then other, and muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to more diſcreet and watchfull ouerſeers: Euen ſo in Benefices or paſtorall charges, the greater cures are to be deliuered ouer to the wiſer and learneder perſons.</p>
            <p>A Benefice therefore (which is by definition<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Beneficium</hi> eſtres Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica quae ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdoti vel cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rico ob ſacrum miniſterium v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum concedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Duaren. l. <hi>2.</hi> de ſacr. Eccl. Miniſt. ac Beneficijs.</note> a matter Eccleſiaſticall gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to a Clergie-man to be vſed of him perpetually for his ſacred miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) whether it taketh denomination
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19082:22"/> of a benefit receiued, or of a charge or benefit giuen, importeth thus much: That Benefices of what quality or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoeuer, can not be <hi>equalled:</hi> it followeth then that benefices haue bin alwayes <hi>proportioned</hi> according to that ſame proportionable equalitie not ſtrict or abſolute, hauing an eye reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiuely looking vpon the deſerts of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall men. Some Benefices haue title of dignitie, as Biſhopricks, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaconry and the like: ſome haue cure of ſoules without dignitie annexed to them, as Parſonages: ſome neither ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of dignitie nor cure of ſoules, but ſimply ſo called. Amongſt which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſome are of more eminency and ornament, other of inferiour and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er degre. Such as are more conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are prebends or the Canons of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall churches: ſuch as are leſſe are rurall Prebends ſo called. Some Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices haue actual or habituall cure of ſoules, other haue cure habitually, and are diſcured actually; other neither actually nor habitually, but vtterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured: yet neuertheleſſe retaine the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19082:23"/> name of Benefices in a generalitie, as our impropriations. Biſhopricks and Archdeaconries are Benefices with ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of dignitie, vnto both which are annexed Iuriſdictionall power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie: ſome other Benefices with dignitie, as Deanries, Chantorſhips, Chancellorſhips, and Treaſurerſhips, for the moſt part are dignities (as the cuſtome of the Church doth beare it) without any Iuriſdiction: all wich in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equallitie is not diſagreeing from Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall policie or adminiſtration, and may ſerue for the better conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cathedrall churches, and other Collegiat or not Collegiat churches or Pariſhes: ſo that many of theſe are dignities, but none are indignities, whoſoeuer ſhall vndergoe the burthen and charges of them.</p>
            <p>If we ſhall looke into the Aaroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call race of Prieſts and into the Leuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call order, it was according to impari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie not paritie. To deſcend and goe lower, if we ſhall looke backe vpon the Primitiue times of the Apoſtolicall men, the times of Martyrs, and the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19082:23"/> next ſucceeding times, we ſhall eaſilie finde ſuperioritie, and inferioritie, and imparitie of liuings. If we ſhall vnfold the memorie of former times in our Church, and the ancient practiſe, we ſhal plainly ſee an allotment of church liuings according to inequality, and that by the wiſedome and diſcreet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution of the Biſhop: all which is matter worthy the deduction; for the Biſhop and all his Clergie liued firſt in a kind of communitie in the city (for in the cities were Biſhops Seas firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) whereof he bare the name of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. He and they going abroad at certeine moſt conuenient and requiſit times to preach and miniſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in the territorie adioyning. At what time all Church reuenues of the whole dioceſſe, whether lands gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the liberalitie of Princes, or tithes, oblations or legacies giuen by the people, were in common amongſt all, but at the diſtribution of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to be diuided vnto all according to a proportion of their paines and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: one part was emploied, <hi>pro men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19082:24"/> epiſcopali,</hi> for the Biſhops hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; another part to mainteine the com-Presbyterie and thoſe of the Clergie; the third, for building or repairing the Churches in the citie and Churches of the countrey; the fourth part for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Captiues, reliefe of the poore, and for other godly vſes. The Biſhops then ſeemed to haue had a large part, <hi>videlicet,</hi> one fourth part, as much to his owne part as all the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie had to their part: which part or portion of the Clergies was not ſo proportioned to euery man equally or alike, but as the Biſhop liked, who in reuenewes of the Church in title as a kinde of proprietarie, of himſelfe did ſet downe euery mans part. But after all this, when diuers godly men vpon their zeale and deuotion to the glorie of God and ſeruice of his Church, and the rather induced and lead thereunto to haue the nomination of a Miniſter, had erected and endowed diuers chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in ſeuerall places farre diſtant in their countreys: inſomuch that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny multiplied ſeuerall pariſhes could
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19082:24"/> not conueniently and in due ſeaſon be ſo often and orderly reſpected by thoſe whole ſpeciall attendance was about the Biſhop, the generall Paſtor of the Dioceſſe, ſauing at certaine times, and that the former communitie beganne, partly by multitude of the Clergie thronged together in one place, and partly for other inconueniences to be no leſſe troubleſome than enuious. Then followed hereupon in the moſt parts of the world of Chriſtianitie, a diuiſion ratable of all Church-reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues: ſo that the Biſhop and the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie which was to remaine in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall church of the chiefe citie, and the Clergy of the Dioceſſe beſides had their portions allotted vnto them, but not by any Arithmeticall equality. out of which euery one of them ſeuerally beſides their owne maintenance, was afterwards to defray for the fabricke of their Churches, &amp; reliefe of the poore, as their abilities did ſtretch.</p>
            <p>My Illatiue therefore is, the Biſhop (as a common Paſtor of the whole Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe, as the common law at this day
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19082:25"/> doth account him) did call other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>in partem ſollicitudinis,</hi> into a part of the charge: the Biſhop by inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them into ſeuerall Churches, and the reuenues thereof, did inueſt them into a title of that part of the glebe and tithes, &amp;c. which was rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned as his owne before: Howbeit at the preſentation of the Founders or Patrons to whom the Canons gaue the preheminence in regard of their coſt beſtowed, the Biſhops did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute them who were of equalitie of gifts, the Patrons preſented not their Clerks to an equalitie of liuings: It ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euery Clerke was accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as was fit for euery Clerke. If the originall Patrons did preſent any, their preſentation was no <hi>maine bar</hi> to other incident preferments. How church liuings fell into ſo many fractions, I liſt not now to rehearſe: it ſeemeth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy found out for ſo many incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petencies &amp; inſufficiencies of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie mens eſtate, was fauor of the law, and the priuiledge of pluralities.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:19082:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of ſingularitie and pluralitie of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and of the cauſe thereof, <hi>vz.</hi> Diſpenſations.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat euery Clergie man ſhould haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petent liuing, that is, ſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and none be inſufficiently proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, hath beene prooued before: that all Miniſters of the word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, ſhould be prouided for a like, and equalled in preferment, can neuer be prooued: that ſome haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioied more, ſome leſſe, in portion and allotments of tithes, oblations, glebe, &amp;c. which I call an imparity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equalitie of Church liuings, is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued nor diſallowed by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: that ſingularitie or dualitie of Benefices which is commonly termed pluralitie of liuings (which is more then one) is deſcended of the auncient practiſe and cuſtome of the Church &amp; canons approoued: remaineth now
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19082:26"/> to be handled in eſpeciall. The points in order are theſe: the word <hi>pluralitie</hi> of Benefices, is not found in ſo many ſyllables in the word of God, and yet not repugnant to the word of God. Diuiſion of pariſhes or ſingularitie of Benefices is not laid downe in expreſſe termes in the word of God, yet a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deducible out of the word of God: Reſidence and tarriance vpon a mans Benefice or cure, is a matter praiſeable with God and his Church, Non Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or abſence, <hi>I meane, not to reſide corporally for a time or ſeaſon,</hi> leauing ſufficient direction and inſtruction for the cure, is not a thing vnlawfull or damnable before God &amp; the Church of God.</p>
            <p>Singularitie and pluralltie of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, that is, Pluralitie and Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, are not <hi>oppoſitiuely</hi> ſet one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other, as either priuately op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite as light and darkneſſe, death and life, ſight and blindneſſe, and ſuch like: or contrary oppoſite, as white and blacke, vice and vertue, righteouſneſſe and vnrighteouſneſſe, or contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19082:26"/> oppoſite, as feeding and not fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, preaching and not preaching, gouerning and not gouerning, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring and not miniſtring, teaching and not teaching, catechizing and not catechizing: although in ſome appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at the firſt ſight it might ſeeme ſo: but rather Relatiuely oppoſite or ſet one againſt the other:<note n="*" place="margin">Relatiua ſunt quaecunque hoc ipſum quod ſunt dicuntur eſſe aliorum, aut quaecunque modo ad aliud. <hi>Ariſt. Cati.</hi>
               </note> Benefice or Benefices, one or more, are a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiated man his Benefice or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices: a Beneficed man whether he take his denomination from one Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice or more, is alway but a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed man; and therefore one man to both his Benefices is but, <hi>tanquam v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ad vnum quod eſt aptiſsimum,</hi> as one to one, which moſt apt &amp; agreeing.<note n="*" place="margin">Phyſic. quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque vni &amp; eidem ſunt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem inter ſe ſunt eadem.</note> This <hi>vnum</hi> (one) is <hi>vnum Regimine, vel Cura paſtorali,</hi> thoſe things which are one and the ſame to one and the ſame, are betweene themſelues, the verie ſame. Logicians doe well know that one <hi>in abstracto &amp; incon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reto ad duo in Abſtracto vel in concreto,</hi> is not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: I will not ſpell Logicke: This is plaine, for neither number is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19082:27"/> to number, nor ſubſtance to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: To reſort to the originall &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Pluralities: it ſeemeth that firſt of al Pluralitie did rize vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diuiſions of pariſhes, which pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes ſeeme diuided again into ſo many fractions. <hi>Dyonyſe</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Cap. Eccleſias canſ. <hi>13.</hi> queſt. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; cap. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoral eccleſias ſingulas ſingulis Presbyteris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus, parochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as &amp; caemite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria eis diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ita vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet vt nullus alterius paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiae terminos aut ius inuadat.</note> Biſhop of Rome, was the firſt as ſome ſay, that diuided pariſhes &amp; appointed euery Presbyter the limits &amp; precincts of pariſh Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches &amp; Church-yards, and that none ſhould intrude or intromit vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other: others aſcribe it to <hi>Euaristus</hi> Biſhop of Rome, who about the 112. yeeres of Chriſt, did aſſigne to euery ſeuerall Presbyter his paſtorall cure apart, with title thereunto, and a certaine limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or compaſſe to take charge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of alone, which was drawne into imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and matter of like conſequence by all this part of the world of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie: for in the Apoſtolicall writings nothing is ſet downe, but that they were ordeined in euery great or ſmall citie,<note place="margin">14. Act. 23. v. Tim. 1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thorough euery Church: which words ſeeme to be equipollent, or of one and the ſame
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19082:27"/> ſignification: one thing by the way may be well obſerued, that all Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, or for the moſt part, grew by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall degrees to a narrower reſtricti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then in their firſt foundation or originall planting they were. Euerie man being deſirous to cohabite in as great neereneſſe and proximity to the pariſh Church as might be, was the cauſe why pariſh Churches confined ſo neere the one with the other, and was the begetter of ſo many incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencies of Church liuings, and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner of pluralitie <hi>in part,</hi> or rather of <hi>fractions</hi> and multiplicities of Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:<note n="a" place="margin">Innocentis &amp; Hoſtenſis post eum in cap. cum ad monaſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um in gloſſae niſi ex cauſae titulo de ſtatu Monachorum &amp; Regularum, extra.</note> Diſtinction therefore of pariſh Churches, is of meere poſitiue lawe not Diuine, and the prohibition to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine two pariſhes or Benefices, was not a matter of Diuine ordinance, but of Eccleſiaſticall decree and conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not of God, but brought in by man, and by the will of him that made the canon, and by a contrariant will may be taken away: agreeable vnto that maxime and rule in law,<note n="b" place="margin">C. de Legibus L. vltima.</note> 
               <hi>Eius eſt tollere vel interpretari cuius fuit condere:</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:19082:28"/> And none other lawes beſides the law of man, doth forbid pluralities or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of more pariſhes then one: it will therefore follow by the former maxime, that whatſoeuer is prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the law of man alone, by the ſame law may be licenſed againe, and that diſpenſations as thereupon may be, lawfully granted for ſuch things as Gods law hath eternally and inuiola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly commanded to be obſerued, no man may by any Eccleſiaſticall or ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill authoritie omit, nor that which he hath contrariwiſe forbidden, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man be put in vre and practiſe.</p>
            <p>And in caſe the poſitiue law of man forbiddeth Pluralities, it doth not thereby take cleane out of the way the graunting of diſpenſations, for if there were no prohibition, there were no need of diſpenſations. Now the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly giuing of a diſpenſation for plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities, affoordeth to euery woorthy man according to his woorthineſſe, and prerogatiue of his perſon, which is called by the Canoniſts <hi>Diſpenſatio Iuſtitiae,</hi> and conſequently denieth to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19082:28"/> the vnwoorthy, that fauour for his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe.</p>
            <p>Sithence therefore plurality of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices is not a thing repugnant to the word of God, I ſee no cauſe why vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euery worde of mans reproch and contradiction, it ſhould be diſſalowed;<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>C. pe multa extra. execrab. de prebendis.</hi> Extrag. fo. 22. de prebend. &amp; dig.</note> eſpecially ſtanding vpon the ground of law, or at the leaſt vpon lawfull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation which is the favour of law. And heere becauſe I woulde not be miſtaken in the matter of pluralities of the ſimplieſt man be he neuer ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant nor of the ſubtilleſt Rabbyn be he never ſo arrogant. I am well witting of this, that <hi>ſome pluralities,</hi> which are grounded vpon auarice and ambition are not only incommodious, but plaine odious,<note n="b" place="margin">Execrabilis quorundam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioſorum &amp; ſacrileg. am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitio quae ſemper plus ambiens eò magis fit inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiabilis, quo ſibi amplius indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getur.</note> and by how much it is more inſatiable it is the more execrable. Euery man of meaneſt skill can eaſily tell them.<note n="c" place="margin">C. ordinarij §. <hi>1.</hi> caeterum de officijs ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narij in <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> He that holdeth two Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices with cure without diſpenſation is of both depriuable, and to be turned out, as alſo he that being ſcarſe able to diſcharge one office, doth not onely ſeeke being vnqualified and vndiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19082:29"/> with to procure vnto himſelfe two diuerſe Eccleſiaſticall dignities but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo diuers pariſh Churches. Neither can euery man of meane skill, of no degrees or vnqualified offer himſelfe into this Court of faculties or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his diſpenſation: for that were as the learned Canoniſts call it: <hi>diſsipatio potius quàm diſpenſatio,</hi> Rather a diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or waſting of the ſubſtance and patrimony of Gods Church, then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly giuing and <hi>diſpenſation</hi> of the ſame.<note n="e" place="margin">Guiliel. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranti. L. <hi>10.</hi> particul. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſ. qualiter &amp; quondo. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſ. ſit facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</note>
               <note n="d" place="margin">C. quia non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulli, Eyt. de clericis non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</note> For euery diſpenſation is or ought to be <hi>prouida iuris communis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxatio vtilitate, ſiue neceſsitate penſata:</hi> it is with a prouident deliberation, not a raſh or prodigall hand to be dealt, and that for vrgent neceſſity or appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, it is to be ſtewaredly diſpenſed not waſtfully ſpent or powred vpon euery ones head or altogether:<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vit. Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatio</hi> est rigoris iuris per eum ad quem ſpectat canonicè facto Relaxatio. <hi>1.9.7.</hi> § niſi rigor c. ſe &amp; in § gratia.</note> it is a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or mitigation of the rigor or ſtrict ſeuerity of the common law: it is for the fauour of certaine worthy learned and qualified perſons, not a gap wide open for all to make breach into.</p>
            <p>Laſtly it ſoe goeth againſt common
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19082:29"/> right, that it emplieth no Diametrall oppoſition againſt common right; but importeth an exception from the rigour of common Right. That which common law or right doth binde pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileged right doth vnbinde, in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fauourable concerning the partie ſo priuileged:<note place="margin">Priuilegium perſonale per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam ſequitur.</note> which being granted to one or few, may not by the like exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of fauour be yeelded to all, for ſo it ſhould reuert to common right: which common right doth not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, <hi>Speciale priuilegium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reg. Priuilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aliquibus conceſſum ſi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteà concedatur omnib. perſonis commune priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiatorum nil opitulatur.</note> priuileged right, and therefore doth not lie as a maine barre againſt the right of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation: but rather the one carrieth a ſubalternation vnto the other, and not abſolute contrariety: neither doth any ſuch diſpenſation make a thing which is ſimply vnlawfull, to be by the operation thereof lawfull,<note n="a" place="margin">See the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the abſtract.</note> but ſheweth the rigour of ſome generall poſitiue law, weighed with all particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities of circumſtances, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof to ceaſe or be releaſed at that time, and in that caſe: all which diſpenſations (vnto which the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19082:30"/> of Canterbury is limited, are not contrary to the lawes of God, or lawes of the land, and hath beene vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally granted vpon qualification lawfull may not be denied to them that ſue for it. And farthermore the qualities of the perſons to whom he is in thoſe caſes to graunt are expreſſed: And in caſe the Archbiſhop would vniuſtlie deny the diſpenſation, there is a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die otherwiſe in all equitie prouided.</p>
            <p>This is a matter infallibly euer true, that Diſpenſations from their firſt ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall haue euerſtood, and euer beene withſtood by ſome maleuolent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the church of Chriſt: All that which hath bin grounded vpon malice ſtocke, and doth riſe from the enuie &amp; aemulation of the vnlearned againſt the learned, and of the vnqualified and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifted men, againſt thoſe of better and more excellent gifts; for the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſement of ſuch tumultuary ſpirits, the law hath appointed who ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence and haue power, and who ſhal aske or ſue for ſuch lawfull diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Chriſtian <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> or
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19082:30"/> Prince,<note place="margin">21. H. 8. 25. H. 8.</note> and thoſe authorized vnder him haue this power, who muſt doe it in prouidence or prudence for the good of the Church. The parties who are to be diſpenſed withall, are men of praerogatiue of deſerts, who in diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and godlineſſe are to ſue for it. To giue ſome too much, and other too little were accepting of perſons; to aske more then a man in dutie can wel menage or diſcharge, were ſauouring of couetouſneſſe, or ſome worldly hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: for the firſt and formoſt of theſe two, becauſe diſpenſation is defined, <hi>Commenſuratio communis ad fingula,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aq. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>97.</hi> art. vito.</note> the faithfull and wiſe Steward of Gods houſe, <hi>diſpenſat ſingula ſingulis &amp; labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem &amp; praemium, &amp; legem vniuerſalem ex cauſa interdum relaxat:</hi> I ſay the ſteward of Gods familie muſt diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute and deale with the hand of iuſtice to euery particular, vpon ſute or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt made, or otherwiſe, <hi>Intuituratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; boni vniuerſi &amp; cauſae propter quam diſpenſat,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Diſpenſans debet habere intuitum ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; boni vniuerſi, &amp; cauſae propter-quam diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat. quae cauſa in beneficijs po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt eſſe triplex Neceſſitas vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas &amp; euidens praerogatiua meritorum c. de multa &amp;c. expoſuist. &amp; Panormi. ſuper tertio de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend. &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus, Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titio §. qui vere. c. extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendae.</note> vpon contemplation as wel of ſome reaſonable cauſe or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and for the vniuerſall good of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19082:31"/> the Church, as for the reſpect of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rules and axiomes of law: and ſo his iudgement proceed as from the face of God, or as the Angell of God, and muſt mittigate the ſeueritie of the law ſometimes, and vpon ſome cauſe, as the wiſe and diſcret ſteward, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing euery houſehold ſeruant his taske and labour, and the congruent wages or recompence of his labour. And as for the ſecond, none are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable but for one of theſe three, or ſuch like cauſes, <hi>videlicet,</hi> vrgent ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, apparent vtility, or euident praerogatiue of deſerts: other diuide the cauſes of pluralities into theſe fiue,<note n="a" place="margin">Gloſſ. verb. intitulata Tit. de Electione &amp; Electi pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in cap. Dudum <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> none can or ought to haue two Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices with cure of ſoules, but where either the one dependeth vpon the other, or if the one be annexed to the other, or where a man hath one Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in title, the other in <hi>Commendam,</hi> or by way of truſt or tuition; or a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice in <hi>Commendam</hi> to a Biſhopricke of ſmall reuenues, or where the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are poore and of meane reuenue, or where there is paucitie or penurie
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19082:31"/> of Clerkes,<note n="b" place="margin">C. Priſ. <hi>56.</hi> diſtinct.</note> by reaſon of ſcarcitie of ſuch men, it was permitted, or vnleſſe as they then called it, by Apoſtolique diſpenſation. For concerning great perſonages and learned men which are to be honorably reſpected with greater Benefices as reaſon ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, they were then<note n="c" place="margin">C. de multa § finali Extr. de praebendis.</note> diſpenſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. But as for all other, which are not<note n="d" place="margin">Conſtitut. Othoboni de inſtitut. ſeu collationib. §. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> able to take charge ouer themſelues, which doe not reſide vpon their cures, which are not within any ſacred or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders requiſite to the retaining of ſuch a Benefice, which doe not onely vſurpe many, but <hi>infinite ſuch Benefices,</hi> which though they would, yet by no poſſible means are able to ſatisfie their charge, which by violent intruſion or ſubtile ſhiftes and colourable deuiſes, doe ſeeke to retaine them, and laſtly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all lawfull diſpenſation hold them, all ages and times haue not onely lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly declaimed, but grieuouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, lifting vp their voices like a trumpet againſt them. The neceſſitie is vrgent or enforcing, to diſpenſe then when many vnfit men are to be found,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19082:32"/> and fewe fit for the gouernment of Churches, and inſtruction of ſoules, which caſe may ſometimes fall out, at which time it ſhall be neceſſarie to commit two churches to one man, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to ſuffer them to be deſtitute of paſtorall cure, and ſpirituall foode and teaching: or in caſe the churches are poore, and one maketh an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent liuing. The vtilitie is apparent when the churches are infected with ſchiſme and haereſie, vpon the new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of which decaied eſtate of the church, it is profitable to plant ſuch paſtors as are able to diuide a right the word, conuince aduerſaries and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaiers, and preach ſound doctrine: in caſe the church of Chriſt had beene tainted with Arrianiſme and Pelagia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme as of old, or Anabaptiſme, and Libertiniſme,<note place="margin">Circa ſublimes &amp; literatas perſonas, quae maioribus bene ficijs ſunt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norandae. Durantus l. <hi>1.</hi> particul. <hi>1.</hi> de diſpenſationis.</note> or ſuch like poiſonable hereſies as of late. The prerogatiue of merits is euident, where woorthy men muſt be worthely rewarded, whoſe gifts are ſhining in the church, whoſe labors are aboundant, the teſtimonies of whoſe gifts is extant in the ſchoole
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19082:32"/> of learning, and therefore their reward muſt be euidently ſet downe in the common-wealth, or elſe none will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour for excellency in learning.<note n="*" place="margin">C. Vbi perſonae eſt bona &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtria &amp; lít<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata, quae meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs ſciret, &amp; poſſet regere duas Eccleſias vel decem, quam alius vnam Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. <hi>4.</hi> cap. cum iamdudum Tit. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend. &amp; dignit. vid. Simm. Angelic. verb. Benefic. verſ. <hi>34.35.36.</hi>
               </note> That ſuch meritorious men are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and laborious or induſtrious teachers, may not ſeeme ſtrange or a paradoxe now, being ſaid long agoe, who can better rule two churches or ten, then ſome other one church, and ſuch doth the priuiledge of diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies reſpect. Euen ſo the tenor of euery diſpenſation runneth in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble, <hi>Maiores in ſacris literis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus praemia maiora poſtulant &amp; plures vitae quotidianae neceſsitates plura vitae neceſſaria ſubſidia requirunt.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Vid. Rigiſt. facult</note> Higher degrees in ſacred learning doth aske higher rewards, and more neceſſities or wants doe require more ſupplies or helpes.<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>verſ.</hi>
               </note> The Elders Doctorall or Paſtorall, are woorthy of double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, eſpecially they that labour in the word: well gouerning is the cauſe of double honour, but with this condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if they labor in the word: where (as I take it) the word <hi>Honor,</hi> if it ſignify
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19082:33"/> maintenance requireth double main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, &amp; as for Honor, it preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth maintenance alwaies, or elſe it is but ſingle Honor God wote: And as for double, it is more then ſufficient to ſome, for ſingle maintenance may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be ſufficient, but not to ſome other, whoſe vertues, gifts, and degrees muſt be doubly Honored: And for this cauſe the Fathers of the Church and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth, although they ought to allow to all their children, meate &amp; cloth, yet out of their indulgence and fauor, &amp; eſpecially for their labor, giue a larger allowance for ſome reſpect or due conſideration, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of Egypt, to <hi>Beniamin</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in meſſes of meat gaue not dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and treble, but fiue times ſo much as to any of his brethren, 43. <hi>Gen.</hi> 34. <hi>v.</hi> He gaue all (none excepted) change of raiment, but vnto <hi>Beniamin</hi> he gaue three hundred peeces of ſiluer, and <hi>fiue ſutes of raiment.</hi> 45. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> And to diſpute with too much curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſitie, rather then cunning, of the fact of the fathers of the countrey, or
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19082:33"/> of the fauour of the Prince, which is the head, in whom Eccleſiaſticall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and ciuill is vnited,<note n="a" place="margin">Sacrilegij e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim crimen eſt diſputare vtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dignus ſit quem princeps appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauit. Dur. L. <hi>1.</hi> partic. a de diſpen. &amp; C. d. per. Sacri. l. <hi>2.</hi> C. de diuer. reſcri. L. ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legij ext. de &amp;c.</note> is not onely temerity and raſhneſſe, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie and ſacriledge: or to reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which the Parliament and Synode which are repreſentatiuely the whole Church and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, hath proportionably laid out for learned mens allowance, in three or fowre religious Princes raignes, and neuer make an end of needleſſe refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, vntill all be turned topſie tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, ſauoureth of Sataniſmie or diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh audacitie: Who may diſpenſe and be diſpenſed with, it is hitherto apparent: vpon what cautions they are diſpenſable it remaineth to ſhew in a few words, all which maketh much for the equitie of granting pluralitie of Benefices,<hi rend="sup">b</hi> 
               <hi>Volumus autem ſtricteque monemus, &amp;c.</hi> Wee will and ſtrictly moniſh and require, which the law doth require: That in euery ſuch Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice from which the partie diſpenſed ſhall occaſionally be <hi>abſent,</hi> for the greater part of the yeere, he neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19082:34"/> doe preach 13. <hi>ſermons in the yere,</hi> and in thoſe ſermons he do reuerently, religiouſly and ſincerely handle the word of God. And that alſo in that Benefice, from the which it ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Incumbent for the moſt part to be abſent or away, yet for two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths in the yere he keepe ſome termes of hoſpitality and reliefe of the poore; prouiding alwayes a ſufficient Miniſter and Curat, to be allowed by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Ordinarie of the place to adminiſter ſacred and ſacramentall things, and able to expound and inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret the principles of Religion, and to deliuer vnto them the Word of God, if the reuenew and profits of the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice will beare it.</p>
            <p>My inference is, if the granting of diſpenſation in caſe of pluralities be not repugnant to the Law of God, if it be allowed by the Canon and Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall law, if the lawes of the realme vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very beginning of reformation within the realme doe giue due limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to the repreſſing of the exceſſe of vnmeaſurable pluralities of the Sea
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19082:34"/> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and doth there ſet downe a mitigation of former extremities and conuenient allowance for a learned Miniſterie, they then do but loſe their labor which skirmiſh with pluralities, or vniuſtly charge the keepers of the Law with the iniquitie of the ſame, or calumniate others as breakers of the Law, or denigrate them with the infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of careleſſe, and wilfull, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Non-reſidency from their cures, who themſelues haue a relation to their owne flocks committed to their charges, who by other deputed order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereunto, make a prouiſionall care who leaue an inſtructing and edifying ſeruice alwaies in the place. All which with the circumſtances aboue rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed being diligently prouided for, I ſee no reaſon to charge pluralities with ſuch odious imputations of abſolute Non-reſidency, or continuall abſence or deſertion of duetie or relinquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the military ſtation or place. Finally, no man (notwithſtanding ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny friuolous obiections and idle colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions which in ſo many pamphlets
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19082:35"/> haue beene throwen abroad, thereby to make abſence from a Benefice hate full, I ſay no man) as yet on our ſide did euer defend an abſolute eſtranging of the Paſtors from their charge, or in caſe of abſence the Teacher being oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionally abſent, may not apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe fruitfully elſewhere and to his owne pariſh by godly directions.</p>
            <p>It followeth vpon the premiſſes, that ſuch maner of pluralities doth not deduce to Non-Reſidency, or to a meere priuation or abſence from the place, or diſcharge of the duetie of the place. Here it may be queſtioned whether Non-reſidency <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſome reſpect for ſome time and vpon ſome occaſion or cauſe, be to be termed Non-Reſidency, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> abſolutely, and whether a man may be abſent from his charge, as theſe peremptory men doe vtterly denie, and we defend in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiue part. It ſeemeth Non-Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie is not abſolutely againſt the Law of God, or directly oppoſit, as I ſhewed before: for if it were ſimplie impious, then for none occaſion, no
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19082:35"/> not for an houre, might a man be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, no more than hee may for an houres ſpace vſe blaſphemie againſt God. And then it ſhould follow, that at no time, vpon no cauſe, vpon no commandement of his ſuperiour, no ambaſſage abroad, for no attendance vpon the Prince at home, for no proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Law to recouer or keepe his right, for no ſeruice of the Church, for no pacification of Schiſme, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation of matters of the church, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, for no remedy and reſtitution of health a man may haue a coadiutor or ſubſtitute vnderneath him, no not an houre, or be Non-Reſident from his paſtorall charge. But this is moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd in it ſelfe to defend, and they who moſt importunately call for continuall Reſidencie in other, offend therein themſelues, as may plainly appeare by their ordinary practiſe, in their running vp and downe and abſence from their cures, in riding to Sturbridge faire or to the Acte at Oxford, or in viſiting their friends in halfe a ſcoreſhires, or in trauelling halfe a ſommer from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19082:36"/> country to country, to confirme the brotherhood, or in lying a dozen weekes or ſuch a trifle at a friends houſe, or laſt of al in meeting together in their claſſical <hi>conferencies or ſynodical aſſemblies</hi> or in Parlament time. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be Non-Reſident is not vtterly vnlawfull, but where the cauſe is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull there it is vnlawfull, to diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue or be away from a Benefice or cure, and that for a time; where Gods law and nature and other poſitiue and prouinciall lawes, doe diſpenſe with Non Reſidency (as in diuers caſes) it is not vnlawfull, Non-Reſidency is there in deed a fault, where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are deſtitute of ſpirituall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and that falleth out by way of euent <hi>and conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A diſpenſation for plurality of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, being orderly ſued for &amp; fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably obtained (with the clauſes afore remembred) doth not inure any ſuch dangerous, or impious effects, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny abſolute eſtranging of the Paſtour from his flocke, or diſſolute Non Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidency eſpecially in a Church as the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19082:36"/> Church of England ſo well reformed in ſuch multitudes of the preachers of the Word, which are encreaſed euery day in time of ſo much knowledge and vnderſtanding of the word, which we haue euery day, ſo as the world gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth inexcuſable of their Atheiſme and vngodlineſſe and prophaneſſe of life, finallie in the adminiſtration and lyturgy of ſo inſtructiue and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying a ſeruice which is read in our ſeuerall congregations, euery day. All the arguments on the contrary ſide, if you muſtre them are few in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and weake in force, if they be encountred as they may be with han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſtroke of Sillogiſme, or enthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mematicall concluſion: which is the fayreſt &amp; moſt compendious deciſion of a controuerſy: and without this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſcholaſticall dealing, all kinde of Allegations on the one ſide and on the other, are but an heape of waſte wordes and the further way about. Notwithſtanding, thoſe opinatiue men who diſpute againſt pluralities haue litle more to ſay then this which
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19082:37"/> hath beene an hundred times anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſayd and reanſwered againe. A miniſter, or one miniſter may haue but one Benefice, <hi>Say they,</hi> for no man may haue more then he is able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, and no man in any meaſure is able to diſcharge more then one, and a reaſon is becauſe he can not preach in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon to the people committed to his charge, as ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> enioineth: or, <hi>in this ſort,</hi> a miniſter is a ſheapeard and his congregation is a floke, and he muſt attend on his flocke and one ſhepherd can not attend two flocks, for he muſt alwaies go in and out before the ſheepe of his flocke. Furthermore the miniſters are liuing Oracles liuely paterns and ſamplers of holines, of integrity, and of vertuous life, they are leaders, feeders, guides, inſtructors, and directers of theire flocks, whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made them ouerſeers, that is to ſay of their ſeuerall charges, ſeuerall congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations or pariſhes, and ſeuerall flocks. Al which emplieth vnity or ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of charge, and not a plurality or
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19082:37"/> multiplicity of flocks. Adde vnto this that to be placed in two cures, <hi>Say they,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prax. Benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum petri Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buffi. de diſpenſ. ad plura Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficia.</note> is marchandize or filthy gaine, &amp; none ſhould ſerue two maſters, God and mammon. So euery pluraliſt is a mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſt by their interpretation. Againe it is to aſpire higher and higher, and not to ſtay in the vocation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are called, which is to tranſgreſſe the Apoſtles rule:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> laſt of all becauſe plurality and reſidency are opoſite and contrary the one to the other and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileably diſioyned. All theſe and the like ſophiſtications of theirs, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, as they thinke to neceſſity of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; that feeding one flocke, or to impoſſibility of feeding, if a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake two flockes, or to inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence or abſurdity for him to be away or abſent from his floeke, who hath vndertaken a flocke, and therfore muſt feede. To the firſt of theſe arguments a plaine anſwere is and muſt firſt of all be granted that no miniſter muſt haue more then in ſome <hi>meaſure</hi> he is able to diſcharge, that is by himſelfe or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient deputation:<note n="a" place="margin">Vid. Rebuff. vt ſupr. in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſ. ad argum. <hi>Nec obeſt.</hi> quod non poſſit vtrique ſeruire per ſe, quia hoc poterit facere per alium: non enim Paulus adminiſtrabat officium perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſi. <hi>Sed per ſuos miniſtros</hi> &amp; tamen ab ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis procuratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, accpiebat &amp; alimenta, vt ipſe teſtacur. Philip. vltim.</note> as for the deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19082:38"/> it is and euer was lawfull either in ciuill or eccleſiaſticall function as when the magiſtrate or Miniſter is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: and that the Miniſter may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is proued before, or if it be not true in the former caſes, then ioine iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue with vs and make ſome inſtance to the contrary, and if it be true then yeeld to the trueth, that by leaue of law and leauing ſufficient direction the Miniſter may be away, and yet receiue wages and procurations and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from them as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> of the Philippians.</p>
            <p>As for the reaſon he can not preach <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſeaſon and out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon if he be corporall abſent, as when a man doth perſonally reſide: a man may preach by word, by enſample, and hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitallity and by ſubſtitution of a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full curator or deputy, when he ſhall happen to be away. the rectory and gouernment of ſmall Villages, or townſhips, or country pariſhes is not as the adminiſtration or dioceſſes of whole cities and Territory, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteh <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> to preach
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19082:38"/> ſeaſonably and vnſeaſonably to the obſeruation of a ſtraiter meaſure: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was then ſuppoſed that in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties all things neceſſary being more plentifull then in the Country, they might by one Benefice be ſufficiently prouided for and honeſtly maintained or els ſhew ſome pregnancy of reaſon, why in very good meaſure, a prudent and diligent, and well exerciſed prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher one actiue man may not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge two cures, being not farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and preach, as ſhall be ſufficient for both. But if in rigor of conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you will needs vnderſtand that which paſſeth al wiſe mens vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that a Preacher vpon his cure muſt continually preach, then ſhall not a man haue any time to Catechize his people, or baptiſe Infants, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Sacrament of the Supper of the Lord, or be allowed any time <hi>To pray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18.1.</note> which he is alſo willed continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to pray, and neuer to ceaſſe, then ſhall there be no cauſe allowed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, no not for an houre, which muſt needs be abſurd: as for that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19082:39"/> metaphore, or ſtrong allegory, <hi>videlicet,</hi> a miniſter is a ſhepheard, and the congregation a flocke, and that the ſhepherd muſt attend vpon his church or flocke, ſhould not the ſhepheard feede the flocke? it may be likewiſe granted, but in ſome ſenſe that Princes are ſhepheards,<note place="margin">23. Ierem. 2. Ezech. 34.2.</note> and the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge, may be termed ſheepe:<note place="margin">1. Reg. 22.17.</note> All Iſraell was ſcattered as ſheepe vpon the mountaines, that had no ſhepheard, that is no King: And ſo is <hi>Cyrus</hi> called my paſtor or ſhepheard;<note place="margin">44. Eſay 28.</note> that is, my gouernour or king: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit for the illatiue heereupon, that one ſhepheard can haue in charge but one ſheepe-flocke, may not eaſilie be granted; for <hi>Iacob</hi> in the 30. of <hi>Geneſ.</hi> kept <hi>Labans</hi> and his owne flocke of ſheepe,<note place="margin">30. Gen. 36. v.</note> and put them in <hi>diuers paſtures,</hi> which buſineſſe might the better be vndertaken by his vnder-ſhepheards. And for a ſhepheard to goe alwaies in and out before his flocke is not euer true,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.20.28.</note> for <hi>Dauid</hi> left his fathers ſheepe with a keeper, and ran into the campe, and ſo ſtandeth charged with leauing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19082:39"/> his ſheepe in the wilderneſſe by his brother <hi>Eliab,</hi> which neuertheleſſe were ſafely left with a keeper. As for that which is vſually inferred heereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they are diuers flocks or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of charges: It is but one charge, as committed vnto one, for it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <hi>Regimen animarum,</hi> one regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or cure of ſoules, one in regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and for that cauſe not the hauing of them both, but not hauing care of them, is a matter woorthy of blame, if they be not looked vnto, neither is it <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> abſolutely euill to haue more charges, or congregations then one, for ſo Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſhould fall into this reprehenſion, who ſeemed to haue or beare a care of all congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, although Saint <hi>Paule</hi> were Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Gentiles Chriſt his other ſheepe. Concerning that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould be liuing Oracles, and liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly patterns of holineſſe and perfection to their flockes, and lampes of light to their ſeuerall pariſhes, it may not be denied: but that (if they for a time be abſent) or leaue a Curate ſufficient,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19082:40"/> perſonally to reſide in their place, all the light of their doctrine to be extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed and goe out, and all example of holy and righteous conuerſation to be defaced, I ſhall vtterly denie: <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothee</hi> whether an Euangeliſt or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, was a patterne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as well abſent as preſent: and ſo both the Perſon or Paſtor and the Curate in his place, may be both ſamplers of comelineſſe and honeſtie to their flocke. It is the <hi>Image of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> that ſerueth for imitation, not the corporall reſiance, and that this to be moſt true is manifeſt in Chriſt and all holy Chriſtians and Saints of God, who haue left enſamples of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, although they be not corporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent or reſident amongſt vs: En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample in this caſe is much, but dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and inſtruction doth counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile as much, which being ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliuered, may ſerue for the good of ſeuerall flockes and diſioyned places.</p>
            <p>Now to come to that obiection which is often obiected, and as often
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19082:40"/> refelled in euery place, where moſt plauſibly it dareth to ſhew his face: God forbid that euery man of plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Benefices or multiplicitie of gifts ſhould be the ſeruant of <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi> it is but raſhneſſe of iudgement of the factioniſts of our time, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne ſo many woorthy men and learned (incomparably honeſter and better learned then any of themſelues) of auarice and ambition, and other wordly humors. We haue not recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Spiritum mundi, ſed Spiritum Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note> the ſpirit of the world, but the ſpirit of God, and by the grace of God are the ſeruants not of <hi>Mammon,</hi> but of the high God. And as for filthy gaine, that ſhould grow out of this ſeruice and paines taking: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Godlineſſe is</hi> great gaine, together with the benefit or gaine of contentation, if we reſt contented with that which lawe doth caſt vpon vs, or the fauour of lawfull diſpenſation, or any godly priuiledge. And concerning the winning vnto Chriſt, and gaining of ſoules, it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chopping nor changing, nor mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19082:41"/> of mens ſoules, but rather there where ſomewhat commeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene party and partie of ſimoniacall compact, and of vnlawfull cheuiſance which the lawes of this land doth moſt ſeuerely both reſtraine &amp; puniſh, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them depriueable, incapable, irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, excommunicable, which offend therein; whether it be to aſpire higher &amp; higher, or breaking off from our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation &amp; calling, for an Eccleſiaſticall man to better by purchaſe of diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for pluralitie, his eſtate, being the ſame eſtate, let euery wiſe &amp; vnpartiall man heerein be the iudge: In a ſetled eſtate of the Church, &amp; proſperity of the ſame, why any man ſhould ſtand at a ſtay, &amp; craue no other bleſſing then onely one at the hand of God, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I finde neither cauſe nor reaſon. To acquit all ſingularitie of Benefices, of auaricious deſire, is no matter of aequitie, or to accuſe Plurality of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe, and that which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, crauing or hauing of more, is the like iniquitie,<note n="a" place="margin">Summa an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelica v. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſcium.</note> for <hi>Vt fructus lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificiat, ſibi ad vtilitatem priuatam, vel
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19082:41"/> ad augendum patrimonium, vel vt lautius vivat, vel vt faciliùs ad Epiſcopatum, vel maiorem dignitatem poſsit aſcendere: cùm tali intentione etiam vnum Beneficium habere de ſe est inordinatum, quod est contra rationem.</hi> They that procure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation to retaine more Benefices, to make gaine and priuate commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or to encreaſe their patrimony, or to liue more gallantly, or to climbe the ſooner to a Biſhopricke, or ſome other dignitie, they are in fault, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire or obtaine any one Benefice with ſuch intentions or purpoſes, is a thing inordinate or of the like fault, ſprouting out from the like root of ambition and couetouſneſſe in any man whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Finally, touching the oppoſition betweene pluralitie and reſidency, or that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or great or migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie gulph or infinite diſtance betwene the one and the other, and irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable contrariety, as ſome in their phantaſies vſe to depaint: it is onely imaginary and not verifiable and true: for ſuch lawfull pluralitie may ſtand
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19082:42"/> with prouiſionall Reſidency; neither is it the corporall abode or perſonall reſidency on a place, but the diſcharge of duetie, that ſhall make anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: neither is it the pinning of the Paſtour vpon their ſleeues, or any ſuch like indefatigable reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of the Rector vpon his Rectory or Parſon on his charge, but the well gouerning of the people and laboring in the Word, which ſhal ſaue their ſoules. Where a mans imployment is any way benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, the ſame is praiſeable and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy with God, yet it followeth not that they muſt be affixed to the place; for neither the Leuites of olde (whoſe attendance was required in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) did lie in the Temple, but had their ſeuerall habitations, and waited in their courſe: nor the Leuites of the New Teſtament are ſo narrowly tied to a continuall reſidency, as if law and nature could not diſpenſe with their occaſionall abſence. Yea ſhepheards, who are ſaid to watch ouer their flocke by night and by day are permitted to be ſometimes away. The Exchequer
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19082:42"/> men muſt of conueniency dwell neere to Weſtminſter-hall, and the Singing men of Paules neere there about, but doth it follow they muſt neuer go out of their place?</p>
            <p>To conclude this queſtion, plurality and abſence from a Benefice with cure of ſoules is lawfull, with leaue and li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cenſe of the law, with orderly deputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: neither doth it inure Non-Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, as ſome would vtterly infame it, neither is it any ſinne or ſcandall as perhapps ſome would miſdeeme at the firſt: in caſe the ſame be an offence or <hi>ſcandall,</hi> we can not doe with all, there are many ſcandalls of the world, and woe be to the world for many ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals at home &amp; abroade: they that are childiſh or rather babiſh will be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized with euery little or offenſiue thing, they who are proud &amp; phariſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call will be ſcandalled alſo, euen at the beſt &amp; well diſciplined things, all emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory men as theſe of the faction will take offence at or vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery light cauſe or no cauſe giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There is nothing can be ſo well deuiſed for the good of gods
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19082:43"/> Church but by the malice of <hi>Sataniſts</hi> may in time be ouerturned, to the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, hurt, and dammage, of good men and to the great diſaduantage of God and the Churches cauſe.</p>
            <p>As for other ordinary obiections which may alſo be more worthily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, it ſhal not be amiſſe to giue pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them their anſwere; let no Clerke be ced in two charges, <hi>ſaith the</hi> 2. <hi>councell of Nice,</hi> 15 <hi>C:</hi> for it is filthy marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize &amp;c. no man can ſerue two maſters: impudent men to euict their purpoſe will not refuſe <hi>omne genus teſtium:</hi> any witneſſe whatſoeuer euen the corrupt and depraued, 2 <hi>councell of Nice,</hi> out of which councell they may alſo proue adoration of reliques, &amp; inuocation of ſaints, worſhiping of images with the ſame worſhip, that the Trinity is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped as well as reproue pluralities of Benefices; let them take better counſell and conſider that which is in the end of the Canon: <hi>in Regia ciuitate:</hi> let no man be placed in moe great cities then one; in other Townſhips and Villages it is lawful,<note n="a" place="margin">Canſ. <hi>20.</hi> quaeſt. <hi>1.</hi> cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus.</note> &amp; ſo <hi>Gratian</hi> expoundeth,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19082:43"/> and the counſell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and the gloſe. A man may be intituled to two Churches if they be poore, &amp; with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, or by way of truſt and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendam.</hi> Touching that impertinent allegation: no man in very deed can ſerue two maſters that is contrary ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, God &amp; Beliall, Chriſt and Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: the meaning is in plainneſſe, and truth, let no man be placed in two charges without hability to diſcharge them both; or let no man make a filthy lucre of his charge, as mechanicall and trades-men, and vſurers, and ſimoners are wont to do. Furthermore let him that hath an office wait vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his office;<note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> and the miniſtery is an office: what of this? The Miniſtery is an office, <hi>ergo</hi> he muſt wait vpon the Miniſterie, and conſequently he may not haue two offices: and if not two offices, <hi>ergo</hi> much leſſe two Benefices; this Paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme is eaſily deſcried. He that hath an office muſt attend his office: this is foorth with graunted, <hi>ergo</hi> he may not haue two offices, this is plainly to be denied. He that hath an houſe muſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19082:44"/> looke vnto his houſe, or repaire his houſe, <hi>ergo,</hi> he may not haue two hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to repaire: or he that hath a childe, muſt looke vnto his childe, <hi>ergo,</hi> hee may not haue two children to looke to their education, This is childiſhly inferred: a Phyſician hath a pacient, and a Lawyer his client, <hi>ergo,</hi> may not haue two patients, or two clients to giue attendance vnto. Concerning the inferencie, A man may not haue two Offices, <hi>ergo,</hi> not two Benefices: although I may iuſtly denie the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent and conſequent both, becauſe a man may retaine well and with a good conſcience two Offices or two Iudiciall places, if they be ſubalternate or ſubordinate one to the other, and the one be not an hinderance or retar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance to the execution of the other, yet I will inſiſt vpon the deniall of the Argument: for if it were in ſpeciall termes forbidden in Scriptures, the holding of two offices, which I can not finde, yet the lawfull holding of two Benefices or the equitie thereof (vnder terms of Aequipollency) which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19082:44"/> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is not forbidden, but rather comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: if all the queſtion be, how many mens ſoules ſhall make vp a charge, or what quantitie of ground in citie or countrey ſhall be the bounderie of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, this is a matter of indefinit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation. In caſe any Clergie man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tromit vpon more than hee is able to diſcharge, he muſt feare the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call <hi>Vae mihi niſi Euangelizem:</hi> of which they would haue vs to be afraid. As for the other, which is the Propheticall <hi>Vae</hi> 1. <hi>Iſay.</hi> Wo be to them that ioine houſe to houſe, and land to land, vntill there be no place <hi>for the poore,</hi> that they may be placed alone vpon the earth: what ſtir would there be if any ſuch cleare place were extant againſt two Benefices, as if the Holy ghoſt had ſtinted them and no body els. Yea but the Holy ghoſt commandeth a Miniſter to giue attendance vpon the flocke: <hi>Attendite vobis &amp; vniuerſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi:</hi> Attend or take heed to your ſelues and to the whole flock wherof the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt hath made you ouerſeers. The
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19082:45"/> charge is controuerſileſſe in generall to the Biſhops of the prouince in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralitie to take heed, to the generall flocke that is to to many flocks: or if it be to the Biſhops and ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of the flocks, and to make them continue their attendancy, &amp; to warne them of Non-Reſidency and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them from pluralitie of charges &amp; flocks, what meaneth the apoſtle to ſend for them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſeueral charges, or to withdrawe them from their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular cures or flockes allthough for a ſeaſon? Therefore all this muſt be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood with the lawfull exceptions and due limitations of the Apoſtles words, and ſentence of the holy Ghoſt: howbeit to vrge a litle further, and to argue on their behalfe, is not a Biſhop or Miniſter a Paſtor or ſheapheard? and the people ſheepe of the paſture? &amp; is not this commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of feeding perpetuall and inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, and ſhould <hi>not therefore as Eſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel ſpeaketh, a ſheapheard feed his flocke?</hi> True it is that the Prophet allegorizeth ſtrangly by a perpetuall metaphor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19082:45"/> all ſhepheards that feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and feed not their flocke: it is moſt true that a ſhepheard ſhould feed his flocke: and how muſt hee feed them? and feed them himſelfe. How many muſt hee feed? All that are committed vnto him: as many as Chriſt, with the purchaſe of his bloud, hath dearely bought: Chriſt biddeth <hi>Peter</hi> feede his ſheepe, the ſheepe of circumciſion, the number is promiſcuous: or a numberleſſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for his charge was Apoſtolicall. <hi>Peter</hi> is not forbid to feed the ſheepe of diuers ſheepefolds which were but one flocke. Our Sauiour ſaith <hi>Paſce,</hi> feed: what is that? feed, or cauſe them to be fedde,<note place="margin">23. Pſal.</note> The Lord is my ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, I ſhall not want, he maketh me, or cauſeth me to reſt in greene pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and leadeth me by the ſtill wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: Hee leadeth me in the pathes of righteouſneſſe for his names ſake: and therefore to feed, is alway to feed by himſelfe, and to cauſe them to be fedde: which is aequiualent in the phraſe of feeding:<note place="margin">21. Ioh. 15.16.17. v.</note> now in that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19082:46"/> ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> Loueſt thou me more then theſe: Feed my Lambes, and ſo the ſecond and third time feed my ſheepe: it is more then euident that Chriſt committed to his charge diuers ſheepefolds belonging to that flocke of ſheepe, for ſheepe &amp; lambes ſeldome goe in one paſturage, but are diuided and ſorted by themſelues. which not to be abſurd is alſo as eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the words of our Sauiour:<note place="margin">10. Ioh. 16. v.</note> Other ſheepe I haue alſo, which are not of this fold, them alſo muſt I bring and they ſhall heare my voice: ſo that ſheepe of diuers folds, may not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently heare the ſhepheards voice: whoſe pains is the greater in reſorting to them: for which cauſe two diſtinct and ſeuerall pariſhes recommended to one man, maketh but one flocke, though two foldes. Which diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhment of pariſhes the poſitiue law Eccleſiaſtical hath deuiſed, for if Gods law had ſeparated them, then no man by vnion (which is pretended) may conioine them, as on the contrary ſide that which God hath conioined, no
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19082:46"/> man may ſeparate. And whereas it may be farther ſaid, euery naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hath his naturall head, and one head cannot be ſet vpon two bodies, and therefore it is as vnfitting in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall bodie to haue more then a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall head, or two bodies to haue one head. It is eaſie to call theſe two flockes after they are incorporated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, and vnited togither, one bodie and one flocke to that intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: but this is an vnproper Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, to call either parts <hi>homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall,</hi> or <hi>heterogeneall</hi> of an entire bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, or the leſt member or parcels of Chriſts myſticall body, by the name of an abſolute or politicall body: and it is al as improper to call the Paſtor of a pariſh by the name of an head. The head of the myſticall body which is the Church, is Chriſt which is the head, and he is the eſſentiall head, by whom the whole body being cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled and knit together in euery ioint, for the furniture thereof, receaueth an encreaſe. Next vnder Chriſt his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, the king hath ſupremacy:<note place="margin">4. Epheſ. 15.16. v.</note> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19082:47"/> whom the Archbiſhop in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, and the Biſhop in his Dioceſſe may be tearmed a Miniſteriall head: but for euery Paſtor or Pariſh in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey and citie to be ſo called by the name of a body or head, is a moſt abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue or catachreſticall maner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: for they are but members of the Dioceſſe, whereof the Dioceſan is the head, and the whole prouince or Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is the Eccleſiaſticall body: ſo that the belonging of two Benefices to one beneficed man, is as two charges to one gouernour, and two foldes to one Paſtor, two companies to one leader, two families to one father, not two bodies to one head. Adde vnto this the many diſproportions betweene a naturall and politicall both head and body, and the manifold abſurdities if ſuch conformitie be vrged in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects between the one and the other: for if they were correſpondent ech to other, and that in euery point, then as when the head is deadly wounded, the bodie naturall dieth: ſo when the king who is the politicall head dieth, the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19082:47"/> common-wealth ſhould die. And that no king ſhould be king ouer three kingdoms, which are three bodies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litike, becauſe no head can be an head of three naturall bodies: Marke this argument of theirs, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectaries thereof, whether it ſtriketh not at the very head. The concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all is, either two pariſhes may be committed to one ſufficient man, which is that we call pluralities, or they may not be committed, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome ſtrong impediment, or or barre againſt it in the law of God: not in Gods law; for nothing is ſet downe of diſtinction of pariſhes in ſo many ſillables in the word of God: for all is of meere poſitiue law of man: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any iuſt meaſure or ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of euery miniſters liuing, laide downe in the Scriptures, but all run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth on in thoſe termes of ſufficiencie, of competencie, of maintenance, of reward, of recompence, of participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of al good things, of reaping tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall or carnall commodities of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and double honor, and ſuch other
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19082:48"/> allotments for the miniſtery and doing of their office. But if they may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, <hi>videlicet,</hi> two ſeuerall pariſhes to one ſufficient man, then alſo diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations are to be tolerated and permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereupon, which is that we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; or elſe a learned Miniſtery ſhall lacke maintenance, (as the ſtate of things now ſtandeth) if they ſhould not be permitted: if one Benefice be not a competent liuing, it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with the circumſtances aforeſaid, to adde another thereunto, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of a Church-mans eſtate. A Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice now a daies is nothing leſſe then a Benefice, and an Eccleſiaſticall liuing nothing leſſe then that which affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth liuelihood or ſufficiency of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing; eſpecially if you ſpeake of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity or of one Benefice: and ſo (a few Benefices excepted) all benefices may be reſembled to the counſels of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Orators in <hi>Demosthenes</hi> daies,<note place="margin">Demoſt. Philip.</note> which he compareth to the diets of ſicke men: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. which neither giue a man life, nor ſuffer him to die. The pittances
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19082:48"/> are ſo ſmall, the annuities, penſions, contributions, impoſitions are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in compariſon of that which was paid in former times: and as for that which is now paid, it is either long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained before it can be paid, and ſo paid vnwillingly, or if it muſt needs be paid, after extreeme delaies, &amp; expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, after ſo many prohibitions, which are common and eaſie, and conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are ſeldome and not ſo eaſy to be had, with an euill conſcience at the length they are paid, that the olde ſaid ſawe is verified ſtill: <hi>Laici ſemper ſunt non modo infenſi, ſed infeſti cleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis:</hi> The Laitie is alwaies offended with the Cleargie, and ready to hurt what they can: they muſt view and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiew, &amp; inuiew the proceedings of the Church: Some few Honorable and wiſe, &amp; learned amongſt them excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this number: <hi>Contra manſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos terrae res fraudulentiſsimas excogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,</hi> all their deuiſe is to diſgrace and deface and put downe them God would haue aduanced.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19082:49"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of the friends and enimies of Pluralities, and of other Eccleſiaſticall ſuperiorities and iuriſdictions, all which impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth an inequality or imparity amongst men of the Church.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it bee moſt true which the mouth of trueth hath ſpoken, a man hath enemies thoſe of his owne houſe: Yet it is no leſſe true that it is moſt difficill and hard to finde who are a mans friends, and who are his eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both within and without the doore of his houſe: ſuch is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuatiue hypocriſie and colourable dealing of one man with another that it is an harde peece of worke to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne friends from foes, euen in the Church of God, which is Gods houſe: Notwithſtanding bicauſe (if the viſour of hypocriſie and other counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance be taken from their faces) it is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19082:49"/> eaſier found out, my enquirie or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtigation ſhall be of thoſe onely who are either diſſembled friends, or profeſſed foes, whereof the one dance in a net, and ſuppoſe themſelues to be ſeene of no men, and are ſeene of all men, the other are ſuch, whoſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kred malice, and ſhameleſſe hoſtilitie againſt the mount of Sion and walles of Ieruſalem, and the builders thereof, as the ſunne at noonetide ſhining is moſt euidently and cleerly to be ſeene. The friends and enimies of Pluralities and Eccleſiaſticall dignities, are of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſorts: our friends are fewer in number then our enimies: Howbeit more preualent then our enimies: and ſo indeed more with vs then againſt vs: and therefore firſt her late ſacred Maieſtie, and his moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and other godly and religious Princes before them, their principall ſpirits of wiſedome illumined with Gods trueth, together with the heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call prudent ſpirits of certaine Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſonages of the Nobilitie and Counſell, and other induſtrious lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19082:50"/> men, affecting a prouident care of the poſteritie of the church, and patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing the preſent eſtate of Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, haue euer ſtood our friends, and euer reſiſted the priuate ſpirits of theſe new-fangliſts, or contentious and quarrelous men: all which eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Pluralities and dignities are or may be digeſted into their ſeuerall rankes, ſo that we may reckon vpon this diuiſion, all to be either enimies or friends, excepting ſuch as thinke <hi>Pluralities</hi> to be requiſite and fit remu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration for learned men, but they will not giue any man a ſecond Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that hath one already, which ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ariſeth vpon this, that they ſuppoſe too great diſtance of Benefices with cure to be inconuenient, or for ſome other conſideration beſt knowen to themſelues, or perhaps they thinke themſelues onerated in conſcience for the truſt repoſed in them by the prince and ſtate to giue and beſtow vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, one Benefice, vntill all be prouided for, and not before, againſt whom I will not argue, ſith they are
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19082:50"/> no way our enimies or neutrally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, but apter a great deale to be our friends.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the multitude of them who are enimies, I may number thoſe who haue no liuing at all, or haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing too too much: they who haue no liuing at all, are certaine penurious and greedy, or hungry companions, who will not ſtay their time, but muſt be preferred in haſte, and commonly before their deſert, and creepe into the world before they are ripe, or flitter before they are fluſh, or runne awaie as the Lapwinge with their ſhels vpon their head out of the Vniuerſities, as ſoone as they ſee a man haue two Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, their enuious eie is faſtened vpon one; which is much to be miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. They who haue too much liuing are thoſe whoſe lippes are ſweetened with thc fatte of impropriations, and they would haue more. They take vp all with the angle, they catch it in their net,<note place="margin">1. Abakuck.</note> and gather it in their yarne whereof they reioice, and are glad, therefore, they ſacrifice vnto their net
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19082:51"/> and burne incenſe to their yarne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by them their portion is fat, and their meat plenteous: ſhall they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtretch out their net and that continually to ſlay the nations?</p>
            <p>I write not this to the praeiudice of thoſe who haue any or many <hi>impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Benefices,</hi> and lawfully hold them although I may boldly maintaine it more lawfull of the two, to hold two Benefices with cure of ſoules then two diſcured or impropriated liuings as the world eſteemeth them; and how they are eſteemed void of all cure the Lord knoweth, but my diſputation is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted againſt thoſe who vnder a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of oppoſition againſt pluralities, giue a ſecret blow to all Eccleſiaſticall preferments and liuings, would haue the tithes brought home from Gods barne to their owne, and reduce all to penſions, and would ſweepe the Church cleane: theſe are the moſt peſtilent enginers againſt the Biſhop and clergy, againſt the Deane and Chapter, that is the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical ſenate</hi> and other prebends at large, all which
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19082:51"/> is couertly vndertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the moſt part by the impugners of pluralities, the practiſe whereof ſpringeth from this originall, not ſo much from hatred of pluralities or duplicities of liuings, but from an intention forſooth to reduce and bring backe all to the primitiue and Apoſtolicall ſimplicity, which without Apoſtolicall and primitiue and extraordinary gifts reduced toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with it, is a fond conceit, and a vaine intention. As for Platonicall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie or Anabaptiſticall confuſion which is the daugther of parity or any ſuch monaſticall conuerſation, which ſome would haue to be Euangelicall perfection, I hope they not ſo much as dreame of, albeit they dote vpon ſome ſuch like phanſied Church pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and gouernment of the Church. But rather as I touched before, ariſeth from a deteſtable and implacable ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred againſt all Ecclſiaſticall ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; ſuch like imparities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they would haue one man as good as an other, which is as much as they ſaid in <hi>Tuſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lans</hi> queſtions. <hi>Nemo de nobis vnus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellat,</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:19082:52"/> let non of vs be better then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And in caſe any ſuch one be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in gifts, better in liuelehood, better in place, or ſuperior in dignity, or in Eccleſiaſticall authority: <hi>omnem exupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiam virtutis odimus,</hi> all betterneſſe or preheminency of vertue (ſay they) let vs hate. Howbeit firſt let them vnderſtand what this ſuperioritie is, and let them vnderſtand vs, and let vs vnderſtand one the other, and then let them become enemies to that which they knowe: <hi>oderunt nos gratis,</hi> if they hate vs cauſeleſlie ſo let them hate. That one Miniſter may haue more liuings then an other and better meanes to liue by the Church. I haue ſhewed before, that in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery ſome muſt be both preferred in liuing and higher placed in authoritie, in a well ordered Common-wealth, and well diſciplined Church, I haue in part declared, and will now enlarge ſomewhat more, for the ſatisfaction of curious men.</p>
            <p>They who would haue paritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Miniſters, would likewiſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19082:52"/> mainteine them to be all equalled firſt either in equalitie of gifts, and equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of liuing: or all to be of inequalitie of both gifts and liuings: or els to be vnequall of gifts and equall in liuing: or vnequall of liuing &amp; equall of gifts; for theſe are the parts: To make them who are ſutable and equall in gifts by a poſitiue or generall law, to be inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and behinde one another in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, were againſt the lawe of diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butiue iuſtice, at the leaſt againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: To make them who come ſhort of the beſt gift, equall in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, were greater iniquitie: To defend all to be equall in gifts and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in liuings, <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel,</hi> were impoſſibilitie: To mainteine inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of both gifts and liuings, is the matter we ſeeke for, and by argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and reaſon, is deduced from the authoritie of Scriptures, and praxis of the Church. <hi>The enemies of</hi> pluralities and friends of paritie, are for the moſt part haters of all eminencie of gifts, &amp; ſworne enemies vnto all <hi>ſtanding</hi> ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie of Miniſters ouer Miniſters in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19082:53"/> the church of <hi>England,</hi> and are in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the ſame, accuſing alwayes the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equalitie &amp; rule which are exerciſed in the church for order and Chriſtian policie of arrogant dominion or Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian tyrannie. For ſo the faſhion is of theſe diſcontented perſons, to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in their ſpeeches all Archiepiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall iuriſdiction in the Prouince, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopall authoritie in the Dioceſſe, or archidiaconall power, or any other ſubordinate authoritie in their limits, or whatſoeuer els branch of ciuil pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; ſuperioritie annexed to their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for the well being of the ſame, and to ſprinckle it with ſuch aſperſions of domination &amp; proud lordlineſſe, as if thoſe callings did affect nothing elſe than terrene glory and worldly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and minde earthly things. The Biſhops are the ſucceſſors of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and are of the better ſort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of citizens, for they are citizens of the Common-wealth they liue in, and are not nor ought to be without all rule and ſuperiority, or other ciuill honour, if it be caſt vpon them. And as
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19082:53"/> for any ciuill iuriſdiction which Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or ſome eccleſiaſtical men haue, it is not claimed by them as due to their functions, but impoſed by the Prince as vpon ſubiects ſeruiceable for the Realme, and for credit to their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as Counſeller, Embaſſador, Iuſtice of Peace, and the like: although ſome of the Presbyteriall faction do call for it as due, and that Miniſters and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical perſons may &amp; in reſpect they are wiſe and learned ought to be of counſell of Princes in affaires ciuill of the Common-wealth, and to giue ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall direction euen in ſetting vp and depoſing of Princes, <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>De politia ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uili &amp; Eccleſiastica,</hi> which chalenge of theirs proceedeth from a diſtempered humour, and abominable arrogancie. And becauſe there are many reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances betweene Eccleſiaſticall and ciuill authoritie, and the exact laying foorth of ciuill authority ſerueth aptly for the vnderſtanding of the other, and for the clearing of the Biſhops and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that exerciſe Eccleſiaſticall iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction theſe many yeeres, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19082:54"/> and ſithence reformation in the land, of the imputation of dominion or tyranny ouer their inferiours, I thinke it not amiſſe (if it may not ſeeme tedious in ſo ſhort a diſcourſe and the rather becauſe I was lately called be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Right Honorable preſence of Lords &amp; other of his Maieſties Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell by commandement, to ſatisfie the ſcrupulous conſciences of certaine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented perſons, who propoſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things againſt the authoritie and gouernment of Biſhops, but in fine, would neither oppoſe nor anſwer in the doubts which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues propoſed) and I will diſtribute ciuill or temporall authority into his parts &amp; differences according to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> &amp; other learned politicians. Authority ciuill or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon phraſe of ſpeech is, is either oeconomicall as that which is exerciſed within the limits of a family, or politicall ouer a great ſocietie, oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomicall is either <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ouer the wife, being the moſt moderate of al; or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the father ouer the children being more ample
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19082:54"/> and large, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is of two ſortes, either of the maſter of the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, ouer ſuch as be of condition free men, and is leſſe milde then the other two, or of the Lord ouer bondmen and villains, which is moſt ſeuere and abſolute of all other: Now for <hi>Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authoritie,</hi> it is either <hi>ſupreme or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,</hi> or elſe <hi>ſubordinate</hi> and delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Soueraigne</hi> or ſupreme is either abſolute called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is of two ſorts, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is called ſeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuriall, ſuch as <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Nerua</hi> and <hi>Traian,</hi> and <hi>Adrian,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> and other Emperors had and vſed, who though they had all autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in them without reſtraint, ſo that their word was a law, yet did they vſe it according to the rules of ciuill ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, &amp; according to law: or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tyrannous, where not onely their will became a law, but they alſo abuſe it, contrary to all rules of ciuill honeſtie and moderation of the law, as the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of Turkes and other Barbarians who reuerence not Chriſt and his Goſpell: or otherwiſe limited by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19082:55"/> bounds of lawes: That which is ſoueraigne and yet limited, is alſo of two kindes, either vniuerſally limited as is the authoritie of ordinarie chiefe magiſtrates in all free co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealths, as the Dukes of Venice &amp; ſuch other as come neere it: or reſtrained but in part, as for the moſt part in all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an monarchies and kingdomes: for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit kings and ſuch ſoueraigne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches, are ſo tied to lawes, that they cannot diſpoſe of their ſubiects liues or liuelihood and goods contrarie to the lawes, yet they are at libertie to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low or diſallow lawes to be made, to enhance or decrie the price or ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derd of their coines, to pardon offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders condemned by law, and to make warre or peace, truice or league. As for thoſe which haue ſubordinate or <hi>delegated</hi> authoritie by the ſupreme Magiſtrate, they may not exerciſe nor claime more then is allowed them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by commiſſion or by law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of all theſe authorities there is none ſimplie forbiden, or altogither vnlawfull, but the tyrannicall gouernement which
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19082:55"/> maketh ſelfe-will a law, and that is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forbidden in ciuill and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall policy to all good Chriſtians. Now to apply this to the purpoſe in hand, <hi>videlicet,</hi> to the authoritie that Biſhops haue in this Realme, a matter of ſuperioritie, ſo much oppugned by theſe pert or rather malepert compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it cannot be reſembled to oecono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall authority (albeit a Biſhop in ſome ſenſe, as a Biſhop is called a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe in charge, and the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of that Church in a kinde of ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification whereof he is Biſhop) and that for two cauſes: firſt, in that his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is not conteined in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of one family, but ſtretcheth it ſelfe ouer many congregations, which comprehendeth many families. An other cauſe is, for that the Biſhops authoritie (which the <hi>factioniſts</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be ſo tranſcendent and illimita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is tied by the lawes, not onely what not to doe, but he is alſo directed and appointed what to doe: whereas oeconomicall authoritie hath no pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like lawes <hi>poſitiue,</hi> commanding a man
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19082:56"/> how to gouerne his family, but onely <hi>Negatiue,</hi> what they may not doe in that gouernment, as not to hurt nor kill, neither childe, wife, nor ſeruant, and ſuch like incluſiue prohibitions: and as for ſupreme power, whether ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill or eccleſiaſticall, abſolute or limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table authoritie, our Biſhops neither vſe nor claime. It is that which they condemne in the Pope, as well for that as ſucceſſor of the Apoſtles, he claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both ſwords, and earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to be his to diſpoſe, <hi>ſi non actu ſaliem habitu,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his owne great confuſion, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for that in matters Eccleſiaſticall, he chalengeth to himſelf, &amp; vſurpeth not onely ſeigneuriall, but euen tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authority, for he may iudge al, and be iudged of none, may carie millions of ſoules vnto hell, and none may ſay to him, <hi>Domine cur ita facis?</hi> may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund angels to carrie and recarrie ſoules at his pleaſure, may pardon ſinnes paſt and to come: yea in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Eccleſiaſticall, may doe what he liſt, as his owne flatterers and claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backes,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19082:56"/> haue ſometimes ſaid and now would vnſay; all this Lordly abſolute tyrannous and vſurped authoritie is condemned in the Scriptures. There remaineth then to the Biſhops of the Realme, none other but ſubordinate and <hi>delegated</hi> authoritie, which they haue partly from God, and partly from the Soueraigne Chriſtian magiſtrate: and this is the point which is not well vnderſtood of the vulgar ſort, or is commonly miſtaken of many ſortes of people, but principally or perhaps wittinglie or maliciouſlie miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued of thoſe who band themſelues againſt the orderly gouernment and fatherly iuriſdiction of the Biſhops of England. From God they haue their authority to preach and miniſter the Sacraments, and not from the Prince but from Chriſt himſelfe, 28. <hi>Mathew</hi> Goe teach all nations Baptiſing them &amp;c. Onely the Princes giueth them publique liberty, without let or diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, to doe that which Chriſt hath commanded: all that Princes giue in this reſpect, is not by way of commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19082:57"/> but by a free permiſſion that with peace and praiſe, with diligence and alacritie they may doe their duties. From God they haue alſo either firſt to plant or elſe to gouerne, and direct Churches planted already, to ordeine Miniſters and Deacons, and likewiſe the vſe and power of the keies, either by looſing the penitent, according to the Scripture, or binding the impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; the laſt of which is done by fiue meanes: firſt by admonition; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by reprehenſion; thirdly by ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; fourthly by excommunication; and fiftly by Anathematiſme, which is the greateſt of all: The three firſt, of which cenſures Eccleſiaſticall are in vſe and practiſe, common to all Miniſters, ſo farre as ſuſpenſion is taken for the debarring of notorious, detected, or conuicted perſons fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lords Supper: The laſt two though by all practiſe of antiquity in purer times, they were principally attributed vnto Biſhops, yet not ſo, but other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word, vnto whom the keies are annexed, might not vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19082:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> heerein concurre, if the lawes of the Church for weighty cauſes do not otherwiſe diſpoſe, which they haue done heere in England as I conceiue, by reaſon of ſundry ciuil effects, which excommunication &amp; anathematiſme by lawe doe worke, and are ſuch as without great inconuenience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion cannot be permitted to euerie Miniſter in his cure or charge, that haue but ſlender skill, no direction of law in that behalfe, none authentique ſeales to certifie of record, nor tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralities to be ſued, for not performance of the kings write, that lieth in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as <hi>De cautione admittenda de excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municato deliberando, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be the points wherin Biſhops au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie is from God, and not of man: But now from the ſoueraigne Prince by the mediating of lawes, Biſhops haue ſet downe vnto them the places where the compaſſe of the <hi>Territorie how farre,</hi> the maner <hi>how,</hi> with other circumſtances, of executing both the former authorities, and alſo their <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> which although it be origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19082:58"/> founded in the word of God, yet all Biſhops haue the aſſiſtance of their iuriſdiction <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> ſundry waies from the Prince and his lawes, for the founder execution thereof, and reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of offenders, as to burne an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, to impriſon a perſon ſtubburnly and obſtinately remaining excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate aboue forty daies, and ſuch like: Laſtly, the Biſhops of this realme haue the heads and matters wherein their iuriſdiction is conuerſant, by, &amp; from the Princes authority, in whom as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme gouernour al iuriſdiction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his highneſſe dominions, as well temporall as Eccleſiaſticall, by the law of God, and by mans lawe is inueſted. Such matters in the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, attributed to Biſhops, are cauſes beneficiall, <hi>videlicet,</hi> for tithes and maintenance of Miniſters, vpholding of Churches &amp; Church-yards, cauſes matrimoniall, contracts and diuorces, matters diffamatorie, where there is breach of charitie, and no action lieth in ciuill Courts, as alſo Teſtamentarie cauſes, which euen at the common
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19082:58"/> law of the land hath alwaies bin made Eccleſiaſticall, both becauſe that lawe hath litle direction in thoſe cauſes, but ſuch as is borrowed from the ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall lawes, and for that mens laſt wils (at leaſt were wont) doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ſundry demiſes for Churches, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, poore, captiues, and ſuch like good vſes, whereof the Church had the fourth part, and wherein Biſhops are intended to be moſt carefull to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter right, indifferently to all for the true performance of the deads will. Finally the puniſhing of diuers crimes termed Eccleſiaſticall, being ſuch as are not puniſhable at all at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law, or elſe are left by law to be puniſhed by either authoritie: and in this reſpect may this part of Epiſcopall authority and function, not vntruely be ſaid to be deriued from the Kings ſupremacie which they haue vnder God. By which matter that I haue hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto at large deduced, may planely appeere the vndutifulneſſe of popiſh Biſhops and peeuiſh conſiſtorials: the firſt wherof deriueth their iuriſdiction
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19082:59"/> Eccleſiaſticall within all Chriſtian kingdomes from the Pope; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond will needs deriue their iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionall authoritie immediately from God, and not from the Prince, and in a larger manner, and in moe matters then Biſhops in England may any wiſe exerciſe or intrude vpon, &amp; make their Conſiſtory or Presbytery a court of Conſcience and Aequitie, a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent court beyond his Maieſties high court of Chauncery, and put other courts to a perpetuall ſilence.</p>
            <p>And on the contrary ſide may eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appeare to the World the duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full carriage of our Biſhops, the B B. of the Goſpell, who draw neereſt to the ancient and orthodoxe Biſhops, as lineally deducing their doctrine and diſcipline, their gouernment and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and other conformities from the Apoſtolicall and Primitiue and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer times. And concerning papall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (which is one of the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) they deriue all that from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitoll of the Pope which they well know, can not fetch his deriuation
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19082:59"/> from God, that is, borrowe of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt his horne or power, which they can not deriue from the Head which is Chriſt: but for factious conſiſtorials and presbyteriall men (which is the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther extremity) they without any war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiſe of the Word with a Luciferian pride (as if they were to ride vpon the cherubins) draw immediatly their iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction from the emperiall ſeat of God, and will not fetch that which is to be deriued vnto them from the Chriſtian magiſtrate or Gods lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vpon earth.</p>
            <p>The former of theſe will be exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Princes, whereas no Prieſt nor Prelate is exempted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſword, much leſſe hath any pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er within or without their Realmes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially to depoſe them, leaſt of all to inuade them, or to diſcharge their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their allegiance, or to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant their liege people to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, but rather are ſubiect to their power for reformation and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of their errours in faith, abuſes in diſcipline, diſorders in life, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19082:60"/> Eccleſiaſticall enormities, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainely by the publicke lawes and<note n="a" place="margin">See the L. Biſhop of Wincheſters boooke of the difference betweene Chriſtian ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</note> acts of <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian, Carolus, Ludouicus</hi> and <hi>Lotharius,</hi> and other godly and woorthie gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours abroad, as alſo by the lawes of <hi>Canutus</hi> and other religious Princes at home. The later of theſe, although they challenge no exemption at all from the Kingly gouernment, yet ſo munite themſelues, and aduance their Puritanicall iuriſdiction, as to attribute therein no more to their ſouereigne Prince, but to be gouerned or ruled in that behalfe by them, that is, to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerruled when they liſt, and to defend the exerciſe thereof by their temporall ſword when as they ſhalbe called vpon by them.</p>
            <p>If theſe extremes be leadden, then is the mediocritie golden which our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend Fathers &amp; Biſhops of the land do perpetually obſerue and keepe: for albeit the Biſhops are Spirituall Iudges and Miniſters of the lawes, yet do they not make any new Eccleſiaſticall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees or lawes, without the Princes au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19082:60"/> both praecedent and ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and in the whole courſe of their function are tied ſtrictly and preciſely to obſeruation of due courſe of law: which if they ſhall either negligently or wilfully violate, it is remediable by appellation. The laſt reſort, wherein is to the Souereigne Prince himſelfe, who heareth and finally determineth by his Iudges delegated. The ſumme of all is this, That our Biſhops neither claime nor yet exerciſe any ciuill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie at all as Biſhops, though it is wholly vnfit they ſhould be without it: and that their authoritie Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call is but ſubordinate vnder God and the Prince, moderated as much as any other thing, in the whole Kingdome and State, <hi>Exactly,</hi> both <hi>poſitiuely and priuatiuely by</hi> good and wholeſome lawes, deriued for the moſt part from the Prince, and reformable by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and that it deſerueth no ſuch ſlanderous aſperſion of <hi>Supreame</hi> or of <hi>Abſolute,</hi> of <hi>Tyranicall,</hi> of <hi>Signeuriall,</hi> of <hi>Lorldly</hi> power or ſuperioritie, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rulers luſt. Let them rather
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19082:61"/> looke to this deſerued reprehenſion, who claime and exerciſe more abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute authority than the Biſhops, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to haue their Conſiſtoriall iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not deriued from the Kings au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, but ſupreame vnder God, and that in all cauſes of doctrine or maners ſo farre as apperteineth to conſcience, to make lawes and orders Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, without the knowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of his Maieſtie, to ſit and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine as themſelues beſt iudge, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any guiding of the law; and where a caſe hapneth with iuſt and equall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion to determine contrary to lawe, to haue their ſentences once giuen, to ſtande in force (though they be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from, vntill they be in the laſt inſtance reuerſed, to excommunicate their Soueraigne, and conſequently to diſcharge themſelues, for that time of all <hi>actuall obedience,</hi> to call their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods and claſſies without the Princes writtes, and to haue the laſt appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not runne vnto the Prince, but to a Nationall Synode. All which if you rightly ſcan them, are true notes
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19082:61"/> and charecters of ſoueraignty in iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, or at the leaſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Lordly or Seigneuriall, if not tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and condemned by the cenſure of our Sauiour. And let no man replie that the bare title of Lords to be giuen to Biſhops, for the ſame without anie authority in that reſpect is giuen to them: for the Scriptures giueth not lawes to wordes, but to the matters themſelues. That is lordlineſſe indeed, when they practiſe and band them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, &amp; confront the kings ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and wil haue him to throw downe his ſcepter, and to licke the duſt of the feet of their Church, <hi>videlicet</hi> the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterie, an Epitome or compendiarie repreſentation of euery ſeuerall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and church. All that I haue hitherto diſcourſed, tendeth vnto this, that the <hi>ſtanding ſuperiority</hi> of Biſhops ouer miniſters, and the other impari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and inaequalities amongſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the word, both for gifts and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings (which are ſo odiouſly traduced) may be iuſtly defended againſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie part, and that the bitter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19082:62"/> to pluralities are fierceſt enemies to all dignitie, ſuperioritie, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the Church, for ought that I can perceiue by many yeeres obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe hatred is inſaturable, whoſe malice is cancred, whoſe indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is implacable againſt this ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led &amp; proſperous eſtate of the church. Their meaning is to haue a baſe and beggerly and vnlearned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible cleargie in the lande: for this cauſe their ordinary declamations are againſt Epiſcopall authoritie and other ſubordinate iuriſdiction in the land: inſomuch that he thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the propereſt man nowe a daies, that, although he otherwiſe be a ſeely man and vnskilfull in his owne faculty of lawe, or other profeſſion, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly falleth out to be ſo, or vtterly deuoid of Vniuerſitie learning, and true knowledge of Gods law &amp; other prouinciall conſtitutions, yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in place with a praemeditated ſpeech, or ſome impoliſhed oration, and that conned by heart, againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Archdeacons, Chauncelours,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19082:62"/> and officials, thorough out the land, and for two or three mens ſake worthy of reprehenſion, is pleaſed to ſprinckle with the aſperſion of reproch all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer Eccleſiaſticall Magiſtrates and Iudges, and ſo thorough the ſides of two or three euill handlers of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall iuriſdiction is contented to wound the whole body of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal adminiſtration and gouernment of the Church. Were it well done (trow you) for the greedineſſe and extortion of 2. or 3. officers in a court, if there were any ſuch, to exclaime againſt the Exchequer, or any ſuch court, or for the auarice and exaction of one or two badde Iuſtices, therefore to complaine againſt the whole bench: but this is the faſhion of the world, of certeine factious men, and other whoſe orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, is but <hi>Canina eloquentia,</hi> they muſt for lacke of matter be euer babling, though it bee but barking againſt the Moone: it is held amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perhaps a point of good pollicy to vſe inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues &amp; declamatory ſpeeches againſt Pluralities of Church men and againſt
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19082:63"/> the faults of other men, that in the meane time, their owne both miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors and miſgouernances, may paſſe vncontrolled, or at the leaſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſpied: now the Biſhops are in high court of Parliament, and in lawfull Synode aſſembled, let them exhibite complaints to their Lordſhips, that there may bee reformation of that which is amiſſe, or elſe with modeſtie and good maners hold their peace and heereafter ſhut vp their pipes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Of ſupportance and keeping the fabrique of the church vpright.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a true axiome which is read in <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle: Facilius eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruere quam conſtrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere:</hi> a man may pull down more with one hand, than he can build with two: or is it eaſier to plucke downe many churches then to build one. And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as many Churches are built to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19082:63"/> our hand, which is the honor of the kingdome, eſpecially the Cathedrall and Collegiat Churches, the honor of which churches is the orderly gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and gouernors of the ſame: Let vs doe our Chriſtian endeuour to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and vphold that fabrique of the Churches which our forefathers left vnto vs, and as neere as we can keepe and obſerue Saint <hi>Cyprians</hi> rule for matter of doctrine and Diſcipline, that is well ſetled already, <hi>Vt nihil quod tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditum eſt innouetur,</hi> and to keepe the vnity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace. The crafty enginers againſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and fabrique thereof, are of ſundry ſorts, by themſelues, for of him I will ſay nothing, who was principal in this machination: <hi>Sceleris fabricator Epaeus,</hi> our late Church-wright, but of the acceſſors ſomwhat may be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. There lacketh not a number of thoſe, who would haue the Cathedrall Churches plucked downe, and vnder a colour of erecting or making of euery ſuch great Church, three or foure leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Churches, and of three or foure leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19082:64"/> parochiall or countrey Churches would enlarge or make one bigger Church, but of endowment or reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newe they talke nothing at all: they would reduce all to penſionary per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: forſooth their meaning is to bee diſcharged from paying tythes. Some doe onely repine and mutter, other vtter their malicious ſtomacke againſt the iuriſdiction of Biſhops ouer Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and of one Presbyter ſetled in gouernment ouer another, as if any of vs went about to make Biſhops Lords and maſters ouer the Church, and all the reſt to be their ſeruants, or that ſome did aſcribe ſo much power vnto Biſhops and ſuperior Miniſters, as that ordinary Paſtors had no power ouer the ſeuerall flockes. As for the Biſhops, firſt they haue no charge but paſtorall, no power but paternall: they haue ſuperiority but no Impery, they haue authoritie legall not regall, their praeeminence is fatherly not maſterly ouer the people and presbyters; of which conſequence is all other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall inferiour power or ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19082:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> iuriſdiction, ouer Gods heritage and the Lords flocke: the cleereneſſe and lawfulneſſe whereof being ſuch as no maligners can well ouerthrow or expugne, they hold another courſe to impugne and giue the onſet, firſt vpon the Deane and Chapter, and Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaconall, and peculiar iuriſdictions of Praebendaries and the like. As it was my happe to be in hearing when one ſaide, that Biſhops hee did allowe with all his heart, and did giue them the honor and reuerence that was due vnto their places, but concerning Deane and Chapter, which is the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Senate, and the true Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery (if there be any ſuch thing in verity or analogie) he could not abide nor digeſt reputing al that ſuperfluous and needleſſe, and not woorth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining. Needleſſe it ſhall be to refute this phanſie, which falleth to the ground of it ſelfe, as a ludibrious follie of the man. As if he would haue ſaid, a king is lawfull, but his counſell of ſtate is ſuperfluous, and may well bee ſpared, a Maioralitie is not vnlawfull,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19082:65"/> but the Aldermen are not needfull, a Chauncellor is a neceſſary office in the Vniuerſitie, but congregations of the Maſters or conuocation of Regents, &amp; not regents, is a needleſſe thing, a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is good, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſultation is naught or aſſiſtance in matter of the church: as who would ſay, it will be eaſier for vs to be plucked downe, one by one, then many, and as if when the members are cut off, the head could ſtand vpon the ſhoulders: or as if one did ſtand alone vpon the ſtage of their enuie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murmuration, he were able to ſtande alone or withſtand ſo many gainſaiers which would riſe againſt him. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably they giue good allowance of Epiſcopal dignitie &amp; their iuriſdiction but they vtterly diſallow and would gladly infringe Archidiaconall power and weaken that firſt. They will make the head ſo monſtrous and bigge that all the body ſhall be the woorſe, and al this to be done by reducing or bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing backe all Church cenſures to the Biſhops againe, whom they will fauor ſo long, and vntill they may tread the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19082:65"/> one and the other vnder-feet, at leaſt ſet them in oppoſition each againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whereof (as I thinke) wiſe men will beware, and a word of admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be ſufficient to any wiſe man, whenſoeuer this matter ſhall be moſt plauſibly propoſed, for it may be ſuch kinde of men will appeare forwardeſt in this ſtratageme, who care neither for Biſhop nor Arch-deacon, nor Church nor Chapter, and are like to thoſe ſoldiors who woulde crucifie Chriſt, ſo they might haue his clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, that is care not for any religion ſo they may haue the ſpoile. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe what they woulde haue or not haue, it skilleth not at all: that which we in all zeale require, is, that the Church of Chriſt may be ſtill cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and if by Kings that haue beene the nouriſhing fathers, and Qeenes that haue bin the nouriſhing mothers, then by her owne children it is moſt congruent and fit ſhe ſhould be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced: and in caſe we honour God who is our father, we may not offer diſhonour to the Church which is our
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19082:66"/> mother: and if we credit Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> we cannot haue God to be our father if we haue not the Church to be our mother. The Churh is our mother ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. epist.</hi> 38. <hi>de Baptiſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>idem in Pſal.</hi> 57. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 203.</note> Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi> ſhe conceiued vs of Chriſt, and nouriſhed vs with the milke of faith: ſhe conceaueth by the Sacraments, as by the ſeed of her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: thou waſt conceaued in that thou receauedſt the name of Chriſt, and <hi>againe,</hi> ſhe is a moſt true mother, which openeth her boſome to all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons when they ſhall be newe borne, and offereth her teates when they are borne. Whether we take the Church for the number and company of men regenerated by the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, truely ſeruing God according to the Goſpell of his ſonne, and ſealed by the ſpirit of grace againſt the day of redemption: or whether we take the Church by Synechdoche for the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors and preſidents of the Church, that is, men ſo qualified<note n="b" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>5.</hi> Math.</note> as <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> doth take, or whether we accept it for a citie or houſe, not built with hands,<note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. de verb. apoſt. ſerm. <hi>22. 1.</hi> Timoth. <hi>3.</hi> Auguſt. <hi>1. 5. 7.</hi> epiſt. quaeſt. ſup. Leuit. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>57.</hi> Pſal. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> which is founded by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19082:66"/> erected by hoping, made perfect by louing, or laſtly whether we cal the Church the <hi>Temple,</hi> where the people which are called the Church are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, that by the name of the church the people which is conteined, we ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the place, which conteineth, or as the ſame <hi>Auſten</hi> ſpeaketh els where; The Church is the place, where the Church is aſſembled, for men are the Church; that is, for a materiall houſe, and built with hands: The Church is highly to be honored of euery one of vs,<note place="margin">1. King. 8. c. 2. Chro. 5.6.</note> for it is the place where the <hi>Honor</hi> of God dwelleth, and which he reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth with his glorie, it is the houſe which is built to his name, and wherin he will haue his name to be called vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the obtaining of his bleſſings or the turning away of his curſes: In which ſoeuer of theſe ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the church is taken, and becauſe Chriſt raigneth in his Church by his word and ſpirit, which is called his kingdome, citie, and houſe, (whereby we learne that it is furniſhed not onely with perſons, but with all things needfull for the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19082:67"/> ſeruants Citizens and people of God, to the conuerting and ſauing of their ſoules:) many honorable things may be ſpoken of it, many duties paie able vnto it. Giue to all men their dutie, tribute vnto whom tribute, cuſtome to whom cuſtome, feare or reuerence to whom feare, honor to whom honor appertaineth: Saint <hi>Paule</hi> biddeth the Hebrues remember their rulers or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that goe <hi>in and out before them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13. Rom. 7. v. 13. Heb.</note> which haue ſpoken to them the worde of God: many duties belong vnto them. For the well being of the church they are to be reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reſpects: Foure things the church may not want as requiſites for the good &amp; eſtabliſhment of the church: Honor, authoritie, reuenew, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie or ſtocke, without the which, the very frame of the Church will fall downe: Whether the world will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor men of the Church or not honor them: honor conſiſteth <hi>tam in honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to quam in honorante.</hi> Their gifts, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, paines, or diligence, and places are to be honored of all good men, yea
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19082:67"/> God himſelfe wil honor thoſe that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor him: if you ſhall deueſt them of authority they ſhal fall into contempt, yea the very abiects of the world will make no regard of them: the baſis of honor is authoritie amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Reuenew is neceſſary, and the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new of Eccleſiaſticall maintenance: they may not goe a begging or behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto others: <hi>Epiſcopus habet pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam, non vt ſeruet, ſed vt eroget,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auſten,</hi> The Orator could ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Olynthiac.</hi> 1.</note> As for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the loue of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney the Apoſtle forbiddeth, but bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or chargeth the rich of this world to do good, to be rich in good works, to be ready to diſtribute to other, and communicate, which is the true end of all riches and reuenues in laitie or cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie men:<note place="margin">44. Eccleſ.</note> for <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faithfull was rich (and as one tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on readeth) they were alſo rich and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comfort other, or mighty in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Laſt of all, the Church muſt haue a treaſury or ſtocke, which is the ready way to make prouiſion for the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:19082:68"/> and widdowes, captiues, and the poore: In the corrupteſt time of the Church, or Iewiſh ſynagogue, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was not taken away but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained amongſt them, in the time of Chriſt conuerſant vpon earth, how much more requiſite is the treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to bee vpheld nowe, or Churches ſtocke, in ſuch infinit ſwarms of poore people, maimed ſoldiours, indigent perſons, ſicke and diſtreſſed members of Chriſt: Here offereth it ſelfe a great ocean ſea of matter to enlarge vpon, but I will conteine my ſelfe within the narrowes and ſtreightes of this my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which now admoniſheth me to be ſhort, &amp; draw to an end: enough hath beene dilated of the imparitie of the gifts of men of the Church, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of competency, &amp; ſufficiency of their liuings, ſomewhat of inaequalitie, or of their Eccleſiaſticall preferments to much, (it may be in the opinion of ſome) of the Pluralitie of Benefices or Beneficed men, a little of the ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Biſhops ouer Miniſters, and of Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction ouer all the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19082:68"/> reſt, a great deale againſt the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and breakers or ſcorners of the ſame: what is due to holy Church is apparent, <hi>videlicet,</hi> tithes, oblations, glebe-land, reuenues, and poſſeſſions &amp;c. that God may be honored, his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters &amp; ſeruants mainteined, Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches repaired, the poore relieued, his Goſpell and the trueth publiſhed, his word multiplied, his name magnified vnto the ends of the world: what is due from Church men, is by the way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. The Miniſters of the Goſpell which will liue of the Goſpell muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their Miniſterie which they haue receiued of the Lord, the preachers of the worde muſt preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon: the ſhepheards muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and watch their flocks by night and day, and muſt feed their flockes whether they be ſheepe or lambes, all muſt be fedde, leaſt their bloud be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at their hands, all muſt be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techized, all muſt be comforted by themſelues, and by a prouiſional care taken for them, they that are babes in Chriſt muſt haue milke &amp; not ſtrong
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19082:69"/> meat, they that are men muſt haue ſtrong meat, that they may growe vp to the meaſure of the age of the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt, as he with his ſpirit ſhall repleniſh them. They who affect Pluralitie and Multiplicitie of liuings, muſt likewiſe effect labour and more paines taking: or elſe it is diſcommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable to vndertake that charge which they minde not to diſcharge, or to feede themſelues and ſtarue their flockes.</p>
            <p>They who deſire ſuperioritie and Epiſcopall charge which carieth with it honor, and dignitie, and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, becauſe they deſire a good worke, muſt ouer and aboue that they go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne well, labour in the word, and ſo they may be woorthie of double honor, teach orthodoxe and ſounde doctrine, conuince the aduerſaries, ſtoppe the mouth of the gain-ſaier, clenſe the Church from Schiſme, and keepe it from hereſie, defend by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preaching the Diſcipline of the Church. And for that they are to ouerſee many flockes, to ſee (where
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19082:69"/> want is) euerie place of their Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, as much as lieth in them to be ſupplied with able Miniſters, and with an edifying and inſtructiue ſeruice: And farther, where impropriations are, and the Vicarages endowed with ſmall portions, and the Donatiues with ſmaller penſions, they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe their fatherly helping handes, for ſome encreaſe of ſtipend or other augmentation to be gotten from the proprietaries and leaſſees, for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation of the poore Miniſters of thoſe places, if there bee no other way or meane to better their eſtate, which I referre to the grauitie and wiſedome of my ſuperiors, writing this vnder their Honorable reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Laſt of all, becauſe it may not be ſaide, <hi>tempus offerendi,</hi> time of offering is paſt, <hi>tempus auferendi,</hi> of taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way is come: or as our aduerſaries more bitterly then truely ſpeake, our doctrine to be negatiue, our religion to be ablatiue: Let euery one doe his beſt for the ſupportance and vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the fabrique of the Church,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19082:70"/> which is Gods houſe, for it is not loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for in theſe daies, that anie newe Churches will be built: it is therefore to be praied for, that we may keepe theſe churches which we haue, which by the ſingular prouidence and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God are left vnto vs, by the moſt famous Princes and Prelates of the land, that haue gone before vs, and left ſuch precedents and ſamplers as will hardly be imitated. The deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and abominable deſolation of the Churches of neighbour nations and kingdomes, may ſerue for a document and inſtruction to vs and thoſe that come after vs, to giue no grounde to any ſuch as gape after the like pray, or would ſo much as make the leſt breach vpon the walles of our Church, by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rupture or interrupture, as <hi>Sanbal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat</hi> the Horonite, and <hi>Tobiah</hi> a ſeruant an Ammonite ſometimes enterprized againſt the walles of Ieruſalem, who would haue the walles that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> built to be ſo weake, and in deriſion of them ſpake &amp; thought ſo, as if a foxe goe vp he ſhall euen breake downe the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19082:70"/> 
               <hi>frame of their</hi> ſtony wall, but rather if ſuch foxes as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues would aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to climbe vp, they might breake their necke: Who were alſo ſore grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as ſom now adaies, that there was come a man, as now the like is come, <hi>after ſo gracious a woman as our late reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Gouerneſſe,</hi> (whoſe memorie be) bleſſed, which ſeeketh the wealth of the children of Iſraell, our zealous <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah:</hi> To conclude, let euerie one of what degree or dignitie, of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer calling amongſt laitie or clergie, Let him, I ſay, do his beſt for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the fabrique of this faire or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and oeconomy, this decency and comelineſſe of Church policie and diſcipline: And let vs all ioine in one with vnanimitie of conſent againſt Church-theeues, and ſacrilegious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, againſt robbers, and ſpoilers of Cathedrall Churches, and againſt all couetous Patrons or Latrons, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers of parochiall or Countrey Churches, the very authors &amp; fautors of all Atheiſme and ignorance, of all prophaneſſe and vngodlineſſe of the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19082:71"/> land, and againſt al thoſe who wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their harts, or with their lips ſay, Let vs take the houſes of God into our priuate poſſeſſions: Let vs holde our ſelues to the ſacred anchor of the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of thoſe things which we now enioy, and (and maugre all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ancient or vpſtart, open or ſecret, forreine or domeſticall) ſhall long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, to the glory of God, and prolong the ioy, vntill the comming of our bleſſed Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19082:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
